<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Penrose Trip</title>
    <description>This website is an interactive portal for informative use, which seeks to open a space for the juxtaposition between psychedelia, science, programming and art.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 02:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 02:15:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Genetic Learning: Smart Rockets</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For me, the level at which natural selection causes the phenomenon of adaptation is the level of the replicator - the gene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Dawkins&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the simulation there are rockets that every certain interval of time are pushed in an arbitrary direction, the objective of these rockets is to reach a target in a specific instant of time. The rockets give a defined number of jumps and must reach the goal just in time, however, they have no information about the position of the target so they must learn how to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simulation runs for generations, and it is expected that with each generation the rockets will become more and more precise in their task of hitting the target on time. The rockets have &lt;em&gt;genes&lt;/em&gt; that encode each of the jumps that the rocket does, then at the end of each generation a score is assigned to each rocket and based on this score the rocket has more or less probability of reproducing its genes in the next generation. The genes are in the form of a 2D vector, since in each jump what happens is that a vector is added to the speed that the rocket already had. At the end of each genetic mix, a certain percentage of mutations is generated in the genes in order to diversify the solutions and prevent the system from remaining in dead ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of rockets as an example of genetic learning is not new, but that does not make it any less interesting. Machine learning can occur in different ways, but reinforcement learning is based more on experimentation and trial-error dynamics. Other learning methods use more direct ways of adapting the model to learn new tasks (sometimes based on other solutions to the problem in order to learn new ones), but the genetic algorithm is responsible for exploring the solution space based on the experience of the system, without external examples of how to fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In proposing the problem, I wanted to find a way to optimize genetic learning, even when this is already a form of optimization. I wanted to explore ways in which the algorithm can be modified to converge faster and avoid classic genetic learning problems in the case of rockets in particular. This is how I got to the implementation of the adaptive response system (AR) and its use to adjust the learning parameters of the simulation automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is surprising. The rockets manage to learn in &lt;strong&gt;most cases&lt;/strong&gt; a route that allows them to complete the task. Some problems stood out when doing a few experiments, but in general the result obtained was satisfactory.
Some of the model highlights are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reproduction-method&quot;&gt;Reproduction method&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evaluation criterion was defined based on the final distance from the rocket to the target, assigning a score from &lt;strong&gt;1 to 1000&lt;/strong&gt;, 1000 being the case where the rocket finished its journey in the center of the target. With this metric, a reproduction criterion was established in order to &lt;strong&gt;prioritize the reproduction of the highest scores&lt;/strong&gt;: a pool of candidates is generated, from which the parents of the future generation will be selected. The pool is initialized empty, and each rocket of the actual generation adds as many copies of itself as its score indicates, that is, a rocket with a score of 800 contributes 800 copies of itself to the pool. Then, for all the &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; rockets needed for the next generation a pair of candidates form the pool are chosen. Their &lt;em&gt;genes&lt;/em&gt; are reproduced using the method mentioned below, and once all &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; genetic sets are generated, the simulation starts over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genetic mixing occurs between pairs of rockets and happens by randomly using the following mixing methods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mean:&lt;/strong&gt; The vectors of both rockets for each jump are averaged, resulting in a set of vectors of the same length&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Switch:&lt;/strong&gt; The resulting rocket takes in each jump vector XY the X form one parent rocket and Y form the other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Split:&lt;/strong&gt; The resulting rocket takes the first &lt;em&gt;j&lt;/em&gt; genes from one parent and the rest from the other parent. &lt;em&gt;j&lt;/em&gt; is chosen at random each time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Random:&lt;/strong&gt; Each gene is chosen randomly from each parent (50/50).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adaptive-response-system-ar&quot;&gt;Adaptive Response System (AR)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the problems that can arise when trying to train genetic algorithms, those that I wanted to deal with with the AR system were two in specific: setting a mutation rate and an effective tolerance range for the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mutation-rate&quot;&gt;Mutation rate&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mutation rate allows to preserve the diversity in the solutions by &lt;strong&gt;introducing random “failures”&lt;/strong&gt; to the genes already generated for the next generation. If this rate is very high, it is impossible for the system to converge to a solution, and if it is very low it is possible that the system normalizes to a false solution without reaching the objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AR system &lt;strong&gt;gradually reduces the mutation rate&lt;/strong&gt; as the average performance of the population increases. This allows that in the first generations there is much variability while when finding a solution, the system reduces the mutation rate in order to converge more quickly in future generations. The magic of this part of the AR is in reducing the probability of mutation as the system approaches an &lt;strong&gt;apparently viable solution&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;likelihood-normalizer&quot;&gt;Likelihood Normalizer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The score is assigned with a function dependent on the distance between the final position of the rocket and the target. This function can be normalized by a number that, when increasing, allows rockets at a greater distance to achieve higher scores. Similarly, reducing this number makes the target’s tolerance area smaller, assigning high scores only to rockets that are really close. This number is called the &lt;strong&gt;Likelihood Normalizer&lt;/strong&gt;. A very large LN allows rockets to gradually find the target when they are far from it, since the score function is visible at a greater distance. When the rockets are close to the target having a large LN is &lt;strong&gt;useless&lt;/strong&gt; as it is more difficult to find noticeable changes in the scoring function with small displacements. On the other hand, when using small LNs it is possible to have better precision to detect the target in the vicinity of the rocket, but consequently it is difficult for rockets that are far away to feel relevant changes in the scoring function to &lt;strong&gt;approach the target&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;issues&quot;&gt;Issues&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system showed that it can learn to find solutions for certain parameters, however there are problems that arise from the same nature of the algorithm and that can be evidenced when trying fairly complex experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The algorithm is good at finding the way to problems with a &lt;strong&gt;single solution&lt;/strong&gt;, however when there are many possible ways the reproduction algorithm generates new candidates that when trying to mix these possible solutions, they obtain a terrible solution. This &lt;strong&gt;slows down the learning algorithm&lt;/strong&gt; for long periods of time as the system converges to just one of the multiple solutions it found.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the number of jumps is very large, the algorithm has many parameters to train and it also usually takes longer. this was expected as each additional jump must be trained as a consequence of the others. But another effect of having many thrusts is that the algorithm may have to find a &lt;strong&gt;less optimal route&lt;/strong&gt; to reach the goal, as it has many displacement opportunities. In this attempt to &lt;strong&gt;compress&lt;/strong&gt; the jumps or &lt;strong&gt;nullify&lt;/strong&gt; the effects of the extra ones, the algorithm comes up with many possible ways that result in a good solution, which brings us to the previous problem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the target is near an edge, rockets that &lt;strong&gt;narrowly miss&lt;/strong&gt; the target when trying to reach it and that could have been good solutions often collide with the edge, &lt;strong&gt;nullifying what could have been a good solution&lt;/strong&gt; only by a very small margin. This is why by default the right border is disabled.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The buttons and sliders of the application allow you to interact with the simulation parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SLIDERS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gravity&lt;/strong&gt; defines a vertical acceleration constant. If Gravity is positive then it pulls downwards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;max. time&lt;/strong&gt; sets the target timer. This defines the time in which rockets have to reach the target.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;# jumps&lt;/strong&gt; sets the number of hops each rocket does. Effective after RESET.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delay&lt;/strong&gt; is the time delay between jumps of the rockets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BUTTONS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generation 1&lt;/strong&gt; sets then generation counter to 1. This might be useful in controlled rigorous experiments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delete obstacles&lt;/strong&gt; removes all obstacles set in the simulation, without affecting anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RESET&lt;/strong&gt; reboots all rockets, reboots the simulation but keeps the parameters set by user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; There are parameters that do not change unless the simulation is restarted (RESET button).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0 / 1 / 2 / 3 / 4  :&lt;/strong&gt; Set scenario.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates an squared obstacle centered in the cursor position.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates a circular obstacle centered in the cursor position.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T :&lt;/strong&gt; Sets the target location in the cursor position.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;O :&lt;/strong&gt; Sets the rocket origin location in the cursor position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/sketches/genetic-rockets/rockets.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
TEST SKETCH
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 08  / aug / 2020&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 00:08:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/08/08/genetic-rockets.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/08/08/genetic-rockets.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>genetic</category>
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>B[ORDERS] : Organic behavior in algorithms</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welcome traveler!&lt;/strong&gt; If you have arrived here it is because you are either part of activity B[ORDERS] or you just came across this post by curiosity. In either case, feel welcome to participate and explore the content of the workshop. &lt;strong&gt;Fuzzy Binaires&lt;/strong&gt; is seeking collaboration and community through their own shared practices of open coding, tinkering and making art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;B[ORDERS]* is an online interdisciplinary workshop program running from July 26 to August 2 2020 in which an interdisciplinary group will question the relations between &lt;strong&gt;technology, orders and borders&lt;/strong&gt;. What can be learned from taking positions that refuse the logic of physical and digital borders?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;em&gt;Fuzzy Binaires&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-border&quot;&gt;The Border&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For centuries, the blurred border between the living and the non-living has haunted every corner of the colorful and growing edifice of human knowledge. Since ancient times there have been stories in different religions of how &lt;strong&gt;life arises out of nothing&lt;/strong&gt; by divine will and, in some cases, life itself is forged with inert materials. Today we know that inert materials, such as minerals and molecules, constitute life itself, and that the most specific phenomena depend on their &lt;strong&gt;different configurations&lt;/strong&gt;. This may have been imagined long before the invention of the microscope, but even now it &lt;strong&gt;is difficult to paint a border&lt;/strong&gt; where the inert becomes life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_7wKjTf_RlI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it wasn’t until a few decades ago that we began to understand how &lt;strong&gt;complex&lt;/strong&gt; the microverse and its rules can be. In the 20th century it was discovered that atoms are not perfect clocks as previously believed, but that they are clouds of probability and that, by construction, they build the &lt;strong&gt;strong link&lt;/strong&gt; that exists between the origin of life and the randomness of the quantum world. A completely ordered system cannot give life to life, just as a completely chaotic system cannot maintain it. Creating chaos is simple, but keeping chaos organized and focused is not that easy. I don’t know the definition of life, but many of us can agree that it shares the characteristics of an &lt;strong&gt;unstable, growing and emerging system&lt;/strong&gt; that combines the diversity of chaos with the coherence of self-organization, leading to &lt;strong&gt;aggregate phoenomena&lt;/strong&gt; that increase in complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the workshop I want to make you question what is your definition of this limit, if it exists, and how computing can open our minds to more deterministic perspectives that can also lead to chaos. I want to contrast the phenomena that can be seen in nature with the behaviors observed in the evolution of simple simulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;observing-complexity&quot;&gt;Observing complexity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following case studies, we will approach two recognized algorithms in computing, analyzing them from the perspective of emerging behaviors and experimenting with the infinite possibilities they offer. The exercise is precisely to &lt;strong&gt;explore the endless analogies&lt;/strong&gt; that can be built between the natural world and emerging behaviors, that is why in parts of the talk these systems will be discussed as simple algorithms, and sometimes as if they were an organism or living tissue. We are going to &lt;strong&gt;let the imagination fly&lt;/strong&gt; a bit and let the patterns become visible through our perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;emergent-behaviors&quot;&gt;Emergent behaviors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key points of this workshop is the concept of &lt;strong&gt;emergency&lt;/strong&gt;. This corresponds to all the properties that can be evidenced in a system but that are irreducible to its minimal subsystems. The definition that can be easily found on the internet is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] Emergence occurs when an entity is observed to have properties its parts do not have on their own. These properties or behaviors emerge only when the parts interact in a wider whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of the workshop lies in our ability to visually explore the systems and intuit which behaviors are not explainable as side effects of each part of the system, but a great consequence of the system’s interaction as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;study-cases&quot;&gt;Study cases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of each case study and how it fits the purpose of the activity will be discussed below, however, the most specific content of each sketch is available on the description site of each one (proportional links).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;flocking-ecosystem&quot;&gt;Flocking ecosystem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first algorithm that we are going to analyze is the &lt;strong&gt;flocking algorithm&lt;/strong&gt;. This is characterized by resembling how birds and fish group together in their &lt;strong&gt;movement through a limited space populated by many individuals&lt;/strong&gt;. Although it is an algorithm that has been known for a long time, it is possible to make infinite modifications that undoubtedly make the simulation more interesting, such as the modifications I introduced to do this study. I added agents that create &lt;strong&gt;another level of interaction&lt;/strong&gt; between individuals and lead to the appearance of behaviors analogous to those visible in &lt;strong&gt;ecosystems&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;special-ad&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://penrosetrip.co/sketch/2020/04/13/flocking-ecosystem.html&quot;&gt;
&lt;b style=&quot;font-size:19px&quot;&gt; FLOCKING ECOSYSTEM SIMULATION &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What behaviors can you identify in any region of the simulation that might resemble interaction between species?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you think this is how some mechanism of biology works?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What SIMPLE new behaviors would you introduce in order to diversify behaviors?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2d-cellular-automata&quot;&gt;2D Cellular Automata&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a laboratory created to teach people with little programming context** how to program simple behaviors** in cellular automata. The granularity of the design allows users to create their own rules for interacting on the 2D grid through a minimal and intuitive graphical interface. It’s also a type of system known for decades called a &lt;strong&gt;cellular automaton&lt;/strong&gt;, which consists of a grid of cells that change states based on the state of their neighborhood. Defining these interaction rules in each cell of the grid creates a system of many agents that interact with a high tendency to &lt;strong&gt;chaos and complexity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;special-ad&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://penrosetrip.co/sketch/2020/05/06/2D-cellular-automata-lab.html&quot;&gt;
&lt;b style=&quot;font-size:19px&quot;&gt; 2D CELLULAR AUTOMATA LAB &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;discussion-1&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you generate a tissue of each type shown in the Lab site?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do you think the rules for conway and conway-4 are suitable for complex patterns?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which applications can you see for this type of systems?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science tells us that &lt;strong&gt;complex organized behavior can arise out of complete chaos&lt;/strong&gt;, as seen at the origin of the universe itself that begins with absolute disorder and gives rise to events like life and matter. With a set of indivisible unit elements that follow definite rules, the universe managed to build something as complex as consciousness, and after millennia of experimentation, it produced intelligent entities with curiosity. These &lt;strong&gt;scenarios&lt;/strong&gt; are replicable thanks to modern computing and show macroscopic effects of the interaction between individuals that are difficult to imagine only knowing the initial programming. This leads us to think and ramble on the imaginary border that exists between &lt;strong&gt;programming and biology&lt;/strong&gt;, between science and philosophy, between engineering and contemplation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How did this workshop change your way of seeing everyday phenomena?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Has your definition of the boundary between life and non-life changed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;let-us-know-your-experience&quot;&gt;Let us know your experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you have learned something new with this workshop, let us learn from you too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe name=&quot;embed_readwrite&quot; src=&quot;https://pad.riseup.net/p/B%5BORDERS%5D_-_Organic_algorithms?showControls=true&amp;amp;showChat=true&amp;amp;showLineNumbers=true&amp;amp;useMonospaceFont=false&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 18:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/BORDERS/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/BORDERS/</guid>
        
        <category>information</category>
        
        <category>page</category>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>art</category>
        
        
        <category>information</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tentaciones y demonios</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The representation of the devil in the Tarot is usually linked to &lt;strong&gt;creativity, desire and carnality&lt;/strong&gt;. Lust and temptation are but facets of an irascible driving force that lies in the &lt;strong&gt;human will&lt;/strong&gt;. Free will is the opportunity that randomness gives us to interact with the cosmos in the way that our desire dictates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;technique&quot;&gt;Technique&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast superposition of more than 20 layers of &lt;strong&gt;convolutional neural network designs&lt;/strong&gt; and recognized paintings in the infernal field of art.
The convolution of most of the layers was done with Deep Dream, a smaller portion was treated with Style Transfer and the other layers were only processed by color shades. The main layer is a photo without prior treatment, so the original features of this can still be differentiated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-artist&quot;&gt;From the artist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model in the picture is a friend of mine whom I have always admired for promoting the culture of temptation. I am referring to the ambit of &lt;strong&gt;reflecting sensuality&lt;/strong&gt; through the mirror and attracting curious glances without involving direct interest. Just as I mentioned before, my intention with the piece is to reflect the &lt;strong&gt;mischief of carnality&lt;/strong&gt; as a side effect of an amazingly &lt;strong&gt;complex mind&lt;/strong&gt;.
I would never consider myself as a model that inspires eroticism, but this does not make me alien to this one. The representation of desire is also an art and although I do not get very close to the conventional representation of lust, the relationship with the figure of the beast is only a mental bridge with the Tarot myth that I wanted to introduce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;models-and-references&quot;&gt;Models and references&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;models&quot;&gt;Models&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kevin Andrade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pictures&quot;&gt;Pictures&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Fall of the damned&lt;/em&gt; - Peter Paul Rubens - &lt;strong&gt;1620&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Defeat of Sennacherib&lt;/em&gt; - Peter Paul Rubens - &lt;strong&gt;1612&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Death of Sardanapalus&lt;/em&gt; - Eugene Delacroix&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;signorcasaubon&lt;/em&gt; - Marten de Vos-Hell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 18:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/image/2020/06/10/tentaciones-y-demonios.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/image/2020/06/10/tentaciones-y-demonios.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>image</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Penrose Trip: A whole new universe</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Penrose Trip&lt;/strong&gt; is a non-profit site whose purpose is to leave &lt;em&gt;interesting questions&lt;/em&gt; loose on the streets of the modern world with the only hope of generating even more doubts. The aim is to touch sensitive fibers regarding the compartmentalization of human thought, since the definition of the line between art and science is challenged. Of course, the strong &lt;strong&gt;psychedelic component&lt;/strong&gt; of this project cannot be ignored, and it is in this context of perpetual hallucination that the aesthetics of artificial intelligence and randomness make sense; in a world &lt;strong&gt;out of focus&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goodbye-old-penrose&quot;&gt;Goodbye, old Penrose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project has been carried out only by me since the creation of the page in the free hosting services of Github in 2018. The page’s first approach was as an image gallery, but with the time it became a gallery of my work and, therefore, an interactive portfolio. It had been carried out with simple HTML pages, with poor Javascript and CSS, and to be honest it was not so pretty aesthetically. This was acceptable as long as it was a portal for personal use, but now that it is more open to the public and even serving as a teaching tool for some Hackathon events, it can only mean one thing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;special-ad&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;

&lt;b style=&quot;font-size:19px&quot;&gt; It is time to migrate to a whole new universe &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-migrate&quot;&gt;How to migrate?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;well, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jekyll is a static site generator. You give it text written in your favorite markup language and it uses layouts to create a static website. You can tweak how you want the site URLs to look, what data gets displayed on the site, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-Jekyll Website&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll allows a simple implementation for static pages that allows to segregate posts (like this one) by themes, tags, etc. It is a simple and efficient way to migrate &lt;strong&gt;Penrose Trip&lt;/strong&gt; with enough requirements for online execution and storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-future&quot;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been almost 3 weeks since the migration started and I’m still getting warm. Much of this time has been me learning jekyll from scratch, and although it is an easy-to-learn site generator, it is difficult to diagram the two-year work again and apply the updates and fixes that have been suggested to me. In the future I hope to have all my work here exposed as well as options so that third parties can leave their contributions to this growing personal project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 18:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/new-penrose/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/new-penrose/</guid>
        
        <category>information</category>
        
        <category>page</category>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        
        <category>information</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Agoraphobia</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2020 was plagued by one of the most impressive setbacks of recent times: the COVID-19 pandemic. With the arrival of the virus, &lt;strong&gt;restriction measures&lt;/strong&gt;  in circulation were implemented as an attempt to contain the contagion. in other words: we are all ordered to wait at home as long as possible. After almost 4 months of containment, it is increasingly difficult to remember &lt;strong&gt;what the world was like before&lt;/strong&gt;, it is strange to stop to think about how the world works now and how it worked a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staying at home has been a challenge to the mental stability of many people who have been subjected to social isolation. People begin to lose patience after months of staying at home, but the panic generated by an invisible killer also grows. Fear of the virus has led some to assume &lt;strong&gt;ridiculous habits&lt;/strong&gt; of hygiene and consumerism, and has even gone so far as to cause a &lt;strong&gt;phobia of public places: agoraphobia&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;technique&quot;&gt;Technique&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main layer is a style transfer applying a &lt;em&gt;“where’s wally?”&lt;/em&gt; cartoon pattern with a &lt;strong&gt;mixed color palette&lt;/strong&gt;. The other layers were different filter dimensions applied in Deep Dream convolutional networks. At the end the image is &lt;strong&gt;processed again&lt;/strong&gt; to apply hue filter, HDR and white balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-artist&quot;&gt;From the artist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pandemic keeps us alert and waiting for a catastrophe that has taken hundreds of thousands of lives around the world today. The confinement keeps us in captivity and &lt;strong&gt;forces us to be calm&lt;/strong&gt; when all the signs we receive from the outside world &lt;strong&gt;invite&lt;/strong&gt; us to panic and disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it occurred to me to create the image I was thinking about how to represent the &lt;strong&gt;state of alert&lt;/strong&gt; from a calm and &lt;strong&gt;contemplative&lt;/strong&gt; position. My cat &lt;em&gt;Pi&lt;/em&gt; was nearby and I saw him observing a feather that fell near the outside sidewalk of the house, in front of the living room window. He was lying on the edge of the back of the sofa, without tension in the muscles, but with his eyes wide open in expectation of any uninvited movement. I found it curious that &lt;strong&gt;despite expressing a state of persecution&lt;/strong&gt; with his eyes, &lt;em&gt;Pi&lt;/em&gt;’s pose never stopped being that of a sleepy cat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a photo of him and decided to use it as my main template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;models-and-references&quot;&gt;Models and references&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;models&quot;&gt;Models&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pi - my male cat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 13:23:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/image/2020/05/23/agoraphobia.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/image/2020/05/23/agoraphobia.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>image</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2D Cellular Automata Lab</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;cellular automaton&lt;/strong&gt; is a system in which a grid of cells determines its state (&lt;strong&gt;ON&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;OFF&lt;/strong&gt;, for example) according to rules established on the states of a determined &lt;strong&gt;neighborhood&lt;/strong&gt; of cells in the grid. The system behaves according to a &lt;strong&gt;set of game rules&lt;/strong&gt; that commands each cell in the grid to adopt (in the next generation) a state based on the previous states of the neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Game rules are codified in a structure similar to DNA. Each cell has 8 neighbors, so there are 9 states each cell hast to handle (including own state). As each one of these states are values 0 (OFF) or 1 (ON), the number of different possible neighborhood configurations, or cases, are 2 to the power of 9, or 512. Each configuration has a response ,for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;if the immediate  left neighbor is &lt;strong&gt;ON&lt;/strong&gt;, then this cell turns &lt;strong&gt;ON&lt;/strong&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we assign each one of this states to a position in a 512-length string, and in this string we store the response, the result is a 512-length string of 0’s and 1’s describing the behavior of the system. This might be codified to be expressed as genes in the form of alphanumeric values and colors. This 512-string is called the “rule code”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that &lt;strong&gt;a single rule code&lt;/strong&gt; describes the &lt;strong&gt;unique behavior&lt;/strong&gt; of a system and, moreover, there exist as much as 2&lt;sup&gt;512&lt;/sup&gt; possible rule code configurations. In other words, there are more than &lt;abbr title=&quot;An octillion is 10 to the power of 27&quot;&gt;10 octillion octillion octillion octillion octillion&lt;/abbr&gt; possible systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In almost all the processes we see in the modern world, the behavior of &lt;strong&gt;organized growth and modularity&lt;/strong&gt; seem to be somehow present. But this is not where this concept originates, because even when humanity lived in caves we noticed the patterns that nature followed around us. In the flowers, in the roots, in the clouds, in the butterfly wings, in the thunders, in the swarms: the world is full of patterns that in one way or another can be reduced to simple modules following the same rules as the system’s clock ticks; the phenomenon can be &lt;strong&gt;reduced&lt;/strong&gt; to the implementation of cellular automata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans are designed to notice patterns even if they are not there, but when they are, we marvel at imagining the reason for their existence. One way in which we were able to explain the reason for many patterns present in nature was to &lt;strong&gt;formulate the problem as a cellular automaton&lt;/strong&gt;, a system of individual modules programmed to follow the same rules that may or may not allow interaction between the agents of the system. This way of modeling complex problems is used to split complex behaviors and define them as simple rules that are repeated over and over again &lt;strong&gt;out of synchronicity&lt;/strong&gt;. An aggregate of simple machines that can express complexity from the interaction between themselves, conditioned to &lt;strong&gt;react to their environment&lt;/strong&gt; in a pre-defined way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intention when creating this laboratory was to offer tools to program the behavior of a cellular automaton to &lt;strong&gt;anyone&lt;/strong&gt; who is interested in the subject and is &lt;strong&gt;not trained in programming&lt;/strong&gt; (Not of all us can be nerds, right?). This laboratory is a simple and &lt;strong&gt;interactive&lt;/strong&gt; reduction of what it means to program a cellular automaton and creates an environment of &lt;strong&gt;free experimentation&lt;/strong&gt;, allowing to propose new inventions that can be modeled at will or found by chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the day to day the idea of ​​cellular automaton grazes our heads and many times &lt;strong&gt;we do not stop to observe enough&lt;/strong&gt; to formulate an idea. Cellular automata are interesting concepts that challenge the imagination and logic without the need to go exclusively into the mathematical field. This universality of applications makes this study area to be full of surprises for those who decide to venture into the dynamic world of modularity and the emergence of complex behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I built this specific gene codification was, in a beginning, a way to &lt;strong&gt;store compressed data&lt;/strong&gt; information of the state, but as experimentation went on I realized common behaviors tend to be stored in the same Gene. experimentation with cellular automaton is easy and fun as long as you find &lt;strong&gt;the beauty of the patterns&lt;/strong&gt; made by simple binary rules. These systems are controversial in the study of life emergence and complex systems, for example, you may know the famous &lt;strong&gt;Conway’s Game of Life&lt;/strong&gt; which is an specific rule code for 2D cellular automata that resembles organic movement from simple configurations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;penrosetrip-automata-tissue-classification&quot;&gt;PenroseTrip Automata Tissue Classification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After playing around with the Automata Lab for a while, I noticed that some rule codes generated systems that grew similarly to an organic or a fabric, as it is impossible to ignore their geometric properties, others only started from compact figures and eventually dissipated. The truth is that I found some common characteristics among the &lt;strong&gt;evolution processes&lt;/strong&gt; of different systems and took the opportunity to make an amateur classification of what I could see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should mention that this classification is based automata that tend to expand, or that have a very &lt;abbr title=&quot;the number of active cells across the board slowly decreases over time&quot;&gt;low rate&lt;/abbr&gt; of disappearance of active cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The approach that I am interested in exploring is seeing &lt;strong&gt;automata as ways of generating fabrics and lattices&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;complexity-and-stability-analysis&quot;&gt;complexity and stability analysis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the complexity of the behavior, the stability of the patterns formed and the recursion in them, I separated the different types of system into 4 possible classifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STABLE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The systems that I classify as stable are all those that tend to &lt;strong&gt;expand&lt;/strong&gt; and remain &lt;strong&gt;static&lt;/strong&gt; in a given final position. It is important to clarify that there are systems such as the &lt;strong&gt;Conway game of life&lt;/strong&gt; that includes static figures or patterns, but  cannot be classified as stable systems since these configurations arise from very specific initial conditions. A stable system must &lt;strong&gt;grow and maintain static conditions&lt;/strong&gt; from a more general set of initial conditions, taking into account what is necessary to ensure the growth of the system (neighborhood conditions necessary not to &lt;abbr title=&quot;all cells set to 0&quot;&gt;extinguish&lt;/abbr&gt; the system).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;centered-square&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;imgsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1H4EHbXa-WZX8G5sX24VWdOQ0JjW9xrrN&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;txtsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;imglbl&quot;&gt;

      From the initial condition, the system begins to propagate and remains fixed when it can no longer expand.
      &lt;br /&gt;
      &lt;b&gt;Genome : &lt;/b&gt;square


    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the complexity of the behavior is basic. It is more like a coloring algorithm than an organic behavior. Systems classified as stable tend to have &lt;strong&gt;low complexity&lt;/strong&gt; since, to maintain the stability condition, some geometric properties must be met that &lt;strong&gt;do not allow&lt;/strong&gt; very dense or complex fabrics. This patterns remain static because the cells that are active continue to meet the conditions to remain active and the cells that are inactive do not meet the necessary conditions to activate. Thus, no cell is deactivated or activated in the already generated tissue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SEMI-STABLE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Semi-stable tissues are similar to stable ones, with the difference that their genome allows &lt;strong&gt;blinking&lt;/strong&gt; in certain parts of the tissue. This blink can be a &lt;strong&gt;cycle of two alternating states&lt;/strong&gt; or a more complex cycle with 3 or more intermediate steps, but eventually returning to the same initial state. This flicker or glitch can only be local, that is, it cannot move through the tissue or spread indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;centered-square&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;imgsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1J4HrzD-704yn9gbxUGuJdibF14ic2VKy&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;txtsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;imglbl&quot;&gt;

      Once the fabric fills the entire space, there is a sector that keeps blinking near the 4 corners of the square.
      &lt;br /&gt;
      &lt;b&gt;Genome : &lt;/b&gt;maze-gen


    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the expansion process I would like to mention two parts of the fabric: the &lt;strong&gt;central tissue&lt;/strong&gt; that remains static once it was created and the &lt;strong&gt;outer frontier&lt;/strong&gt; that is constantly expanding, generating the static part of the interior according to vicinity present in inner tissue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ORGANIC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;how to define an organic behavior? I could say that it is any system that despite being erratic, asymmetric and with irregular density can generate regions with stable, semi-stable and abstract patterns. An example of these systems is the conway game of life, which as its name implies, can be seen as an analogy to the behavior of life itself in terms of the possible configurations achieved by the system. This system can present events of self-replicating, mobile, static or alternating organisms, among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;centered-square&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;imgsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1L7Fv-pLOcPHFcVbfmq1g5QQZj_9G4J8R&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;txtsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;imglbl&quot;&gt;

      With the advance of time you can see a centered spiral pattern. Static and alternating cells are observed, as well as erratic regions.
      &lt;br /&gt;
      &lt;b&gt;Genome : &lt;/b&gt;tissue

    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect to consider is that these systems can decay (gradually reducing their activity until equilibrium is reached) or become unstable (filling the space without reaching equilibrium). I named the example above &lt;strong&gt;tissue&lt;/strong&gt; because with a dense initial condition it amplifies what appears to be an abstract system with a tendency to &lt;em&gt;rotate&lt;/em&gt; and which gradually &lt;em&gt;dies&lt;/em&gt; (as living tissue) leaving behind a stable or semi-stable system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m talking about systems whose &lt;strong&gt;complexity&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;specificity&lt;/strong&gt; increases so much, that they no longer generate geometric patterns or lattices, and have an &lt;strong&gt;apparently random behavior&lt;/strong&gt; (although we already know that it is not). Here I classified all the systems whose &lt;strong&gt;patterns are not recognizable&lt;/strong&gt; and you cannot see an ordered growth pattern. There are cases, such as the one shown below, where growth is almost unidirectional but still &lt;strong&gt;erratic&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;centered-square&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;imgsq&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1i0kMgLLM2aGmFxhQ7yLoeOaXYWG6wZpr&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;txtsq&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p class=&quot;imglbl&quot;&gt;

        You can see the apparently random progress of the system. In this particular case, growth is upwards, since usually the expansion occurs in all directions. A random &lt;abbr title=&quot;rule code&quot;&gt;genome&lt;/abbr&gt; was used.
        &lt;br /&gt;
        &lt;b&gt;Genome : &lt;/b&gt; (random genome)


      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a genome is randomly generated with 0 or 1 in any of the 512 positions, the behavior obtained is usually erratic, and therefore it is a system of this classification. Although these &lt;strong&gt;highly complex behaviors&lt;/strong&gt; could have some very specific utility, the truth is that it is almost certain that any random genome will end up in &lt;strong&gt;noise&lt;/strong&gt;. I see this as an insight into the relevance of automata in the approach to life itself: as in life, generating chaos is easy, but generating &lt;strong&gt;structured chaos&lt;/strong&gt; is hardly a possibility among billions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENTER&lt;/strong&gt; : Runs/Stops the simulation .&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; : Create random rule code (Random DNA button).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt; : Evolves a single step (Step button).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; : Toogles bombing (switch random cell every generation).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; : Mutates a random gene.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; : Switches the state of a random cell.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; : Sets all cells to OFF (Blank button).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; : Inverts the value of every cell.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt; : Sets the center Cell to ON.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;H / V / D / A&lt;/strong&gt; : Sets an alternating pattern along the central (Horizontal / Vertical / Diagonal / Antidiagonal) respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0 / Z&lt;/strong&gt; : create a rule code with only 0 / 1 respectively (Empty DNA button).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1/2/3/4/5&lt;/strong&gt; : Sets a figure of ON cells in the center.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/sketches/cellular-automata/2d-cellular-automata.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
TEST SKETCH
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 09  / may / 2020&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:02:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/05/06/2D-cellular-automata-lab.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/05/06/2D-cellular-automata-lab.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>automata</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Flocking Ecosystem</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If we reduce life to its most &lt;strong&gt;essential components&lt;/strong&gt;, exploring the multiverse of possible interaction mechanisms becomes more intuitive when viewing each part of the whole as a simple set of &lt;strong&gt;binary rules&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swarming behavior&lt;/strong&gt; is a pattern familiar to everyone with a pair of eyes and which we can easily recognize in a flock of birds or in a school of fish, that’s why it’s called &lt;strong&gt;Flocking algorithm&lt;/strong&gt;. The truth is that this &lt;strong&gt;complex behavior&lt;/strong&gt; can arise from three simple orders that govern each individual of the simulation: a point entity (or &lt;em&gt;Boid&lt;/em&gt;) in a 2D space with a velocity vector assigned and is &lt;strong&gt;only aware of its close vicinity&lt;/strong&gt;, as well as the velocity vector of its neighbors. These three orders to &lt;em&gt;rule them all&lt;/em&gt; are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Separation :&lt;/strong&gt; Avoid crowding neighbors (short range repulsion)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alignment :&lt;/strong&gt; Steer towards average heading of neighbors (align the velocity vector)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cohesion :&lt;/strong&gt; Steer towards average position of neighbors (long range attraction)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Steering&lt;/em&gt; is applying an acceleration vector, which is a result of polling the positions and velocities of the near neighbors, to the actual velocity of the boid. All the boids follow these instructions in an infinite loop, updating steer, velocity and position values according to their current vicinity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When dozens of boids are left to wander a 2D space with  &lt;abbr title=&quot;what goes out  of one edge, comes in through the opposite edge&quot;&gt;periodic conditions&lt;/abbr&gt;, they start forming swarm-like groups that move coherently. There can be many swarms in the space and furthermore, these groups are not stable in population since colliding groups or swarms that pass near enough may change the group dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of behavior and rules have been studied for decades: it has been studied as &lt;em&gt;flocking&lt;/em&gt; in multiple scenarios, dimensions and rule variations. The original architecture of the flocking algorithm I used is based on the one developed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://natureofcode.com/book/chapter-6-autonomous-agents/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Daniel Shiffman&lt;/a&gt; in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mhjuuHl6qHM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Flocking behavior was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=86iQiV3-3IA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;simulated&lt;/a&gt; on a computer in &lt;strong&gt;1987&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Craig Reynolds&lt;/strong&gt; with his simulation program, &lt;strong&gt;Boids&lt;/strong&gt;. This program simulates simple agents (boids) that are allowed to move according to a &lt;strong&gt;set of basic rules&lt;/strong&gt;. The result is akin to a flock of birds, a school of fish, or a swarm of insects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;– Wikipedia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/sketch-organism-img1.png&quot; alt=&quot;image of boid system&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My contribution to the algorithm with which this sketch works consists of special boids that have the ability to change an internal state of normal boids, these special new boids are going to be called &lt;strong&gt;Shifters&lt;/strong&gt;, since they shift their neighbors. There are three types of Shifters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They freeze boids (or reduce their mobility) and turn them blue, allowing them to create connections with other nearby blue boids. This makes it look like the knitter is knitting a net.
heal infected boids (red or blue). They can steal speed from nearby boids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Flockers:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; They infect boids by turning them red and more strongly linked to other red boids. This causes them to behave as a tightly bound unit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;Knitters:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; They freeze boids (or reduce their mobility) and turn them blue, allowing them to create connections with other nearby blue boids. This makes it look like the knitter is &lt;em&gt;knitting&lt;/em&gt; a net &lt;sub&gt;(pun not intended)&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Healers:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; They heal infected boids (red or blue). They can steal speed from nearby boids. They may also switch velocities direction (but not magnitude) with a boid while interacting with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shifters do not like to interact with shifters of different species, but interact normally with same species shifters and other boids. They have a contagion probability associated, which means that not all interactions will result in a contagion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;centered-square&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;imgsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1TxDtJudL1pgXbPRGdMzSQSEQZiVrP-t5&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;txtsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;imglbl&quot;&gt;

      Flocker capturing healthy boids, increasing their maximum speed limit.
      &lt;br /&gt;
      &lt;b&gt;FLocker&lt;/b&gt;


    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;centered-square&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;imgsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1efg_KjIO0358kGxBfjKGicmZmTF2VMcY&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;txtsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;imglbl&quot;&gt;

      Knitter creating a network of static boids.
      &lt;br /&gt;
      &lt;b&gt;Knitter &lt;/b&gt;


    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;centered-square&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;imgsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1zkpLejHzpuERPIEFmgfoUZeo6NcHe1y_&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;txtsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;imglbl&quot;&gt;

      Healer liberating some boids form a knitter's net.
      &lt;br /&gt;
      &lt;b&gt;Healer&lt;/b&gt;


    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I knew what programming is, I have learned a few interesting concepts here and there, but over time and reviewing the development that my sketches have led, I have noticed something quite obvious now: I am low-key obsessed with &lt;strong&gt;random behaviors&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;emergence of complexity&lt;/strong&gt;. The flocking algorithm is characterized because it precisely achieves this task:  to represent an &lt;strong&gt;aggregate, complex and organic behavior&lt;/strong&gt; that arises from individuals following simple rules and interacting in the same space. And well, it has been known for a long time that it is beautiful and that it seems like happy little birds and fish moving in a group, but only doing that can not escalate more when it comes to complexity and can not give birth to &lt;strong&gt;unexpected behavior&lt;/strong&gt;. The flocking simulation is a wonderful concept in the study of the &lt;strong&gt;reduction of natural phenomena&lt;/strong&gt; through programming, but it also leaves you with a mouthful of so many potential uses that just sticking with the original rules would be a waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that the proposal will generate new discussions around the &lt;strong&gt;organic behavior&lt;/strong&gt; of autonomous agents with simple programming. There are perspectives that reconcile programming and logic with nature and all its splendor, and &lt;strong&gt;generating a dialogue&lt;/strong&gt; about it is the first step in asking the right questions that point in more &lt;strong&gt;interesting directions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the introduction of the new boids, new parameters are added to the simulation and therefore the behavior grows in complexity. When I did the first experiment I was surprised because, despite not knowing what to expect, I found new behaviors that my human perception was able to recognize and that, unless they are products of my volatile imagination, represent a new way of &lt;strong&gt;adding complexity&lt;/strong&gt; to the system. A few insights of what can be noticed at a glance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flockers and healers can each form groups of boids around them, moving as a group that can affect more boids. Despite the fact that flockers and healers cannot interact with each other (and even repel each other a little), certainly the groups formed by these can be brought together in &lt;strong&gt;larger groups&lt;/strong&gt; where boids, flockers and healers &lt;strong&gt;coexist&lt;/strong&gt;, using cohesion with the normal boids as a force that &lt;strong&gt;counteracts&lt;/strong&gt; the aforementioned repulsion. I like to think of this scenario as a reduced case of &lt;em&gt;symbiosis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;knitters freeze boids that, if they are very close to other frozen boids, are connected between them with a line (the connection or lack of it does not affect the simulation at all, it is just a visual element). When solitary moving boids (healthy or infected by flockers) pass near these nets they naturally try to react at the speed of their neighbors. These, when stopped or moving very slowly, cause the boid to stop as well, &lt;strong&gt;being trapped&lt;/strong&gt; by the static influence of the network.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knitters usually stay near the net as an effect of the net static influence, but not always they remain static as trapped boids. They keep moving in the net surroundings until a boid gets near enough to interact and modify the knitter velocity. This perturbation, in addition with the aligning force present in every boid, causes the knitter to stop being &lt;em&gt;dormant&lt;/em&gt; and ‘Hunt’ new boids that get stuck in the near net. Sometimes perturbations in a far point in the net are propagated due to the proximity of the &lt;em&gt;net boids&lt;/em&gt; between them, causing the dormant knitter to react even if the new boid is trapped not so near.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Healers may pass through small healthy groups of boids, even using its boids to &lt;strong&gt;catapult themselves forward&lt;/strong&gt; by stealing speed. Bigger groups catch the healers easier and since it &lt;strong&gt;usually swaps speeds&lt;/strong&gt; with his neighbors, having a healer within the group usually &lt;strong&gt;helps keeping boids aligned&lt;/strong&gt; in the same direction. This feature also represents &lt;strong&gt;formation of larger groups&lt;/strong&gt; when there are flockers and healers within the group, since flockers are more likely to separate form the group due to weak aligning.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1owqoA1obd-6JPDQjLsrc80o5BQHm-nsk&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DRAG the cursor through the screen to generate new neutral boids pointed in random directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates Flocker in the cursor current position&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;H :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates Healer in the cursor current position&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates Knitter in the cursor current position&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mobile&quot;&gt;Mobile&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TOUCH AND DRAG to create new boids.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SHAKE device to create random shifter in random XY position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/sketches/flocking-ecosystem/flocking-ecosystem.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
TEST SKETCH
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 13  / apr / 2020&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 02:20:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/04/13/flocking-ecosystem.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/04/13/flocking-ecosystem.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>space</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>random</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>IMFERYE: A quest for legacy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;a group of settlers is left in an unexplored world with the aim of creating a global empire over the years. Name unexplored terrain, evolve your cities and above all have fun creating an empire as big as you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;random map&lt;/strong&gt; is generated using Perlin’s Noise including random resource sources in the field. The resource field is also generated using perlin noise but using a detail index more suitable for smaller sports (more detail in noise shape). The game maintains randomness to generate many elements of the game such as events and map conditions among other things, however, other elements such as names depend on a component associated with the immediately previous city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each town &lt;strong&gt;consumes&lt;/strong&gt; according to its size and is also capable of producing &lt;strong&gt;resources&lt;/strong&gt; if it’s on a resource spot The idea of the game is to &lt;strong&gt;expand the empire&lt;/strong&gt; as much as possible without being consumed by its own size, taking into account &lt;strong&gt;unexpected events&lt;/strong&gt; and quick growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything, except the creation of new towns, is generated with &lt;strong&gt;random numbers&lt;/strong&gt; or has to do with some random value. This is an interesting feature because it allows you to have a &lt;strong&gt;variety of situations&lt;/strong&gt; within the framework of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially when I created the project I wanted to practice a new concept that I just learned: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perlin_noise&quot;&gt;Perlin’s noise&lt;/a&gt;. An interesting concept for &lt;strong&gt;someone who loves randomness as much as I do&lt;/strong&gt;, since it is noise that is &lt;strong&gt;locally consistent&lt;/strong&gt; but &lt;strong&gt;globally random&lt;/strong&gt;. Putting it to the test I realized that in two dimensions it is easy to create cut points in the magnitude of the noise, thus creating borders on the 2D surface that enclose spots and their size depends on the cut point.
These spots turned them into islands and eventually continents. From there it was easy to start due to the structure of objects subjected to the random map map generated. The project was refined on several occasions until it became the Imferye that it is now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I directed the project in this direction because it gave me a bit of morbidity to think about our &lt;strong&gt;history as an intelligent species&lt;/strong&gt; on planet earth, and how much of that history we have lost at the hands of violent humanity, unexpected events or even bad luck. &lt;strong&gt;Modeling the legacy&lt;/strong&gt; as a way to quantify lost culture seems to me one of the most interesting details of the game: being able to observe the reasons why a civilization can put aside its most historic cities for important reasons and thus losing legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to think that the format of the game helps to &lt;strong&gt;pose the growth of a civilization as an expansion&lt;/strong&gt; originated in a center, a cancer of roads and houses that expands through unexplored terrain. Based on these ideas, I imagine how the names of cities are established in the legacy of those who founded them, in how tradition and language are &lt;strong&gt;dragged and mutated&lt;/strong&gt; by an accelerated expansion to the rhythm of consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more literary sense that the game has, I also wanted to pose a &lt;strong&gt;management challenge&lt;/strong&gt; to anyone who dares to play it. The game puts the player in a situation where  &lt;strong&gt;not always&lt;/strong&gt; taking  the most intuitive choices  prevent the empire from falling apart. The game itself is not the great strategy puzzle, but considering that it was done by one person on p5 I can say that I am proud of this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game ended up being everything I had hoped for: an alive puzzle and a temporary pet. The estimated playing time is &lt;strong&gt;half an hour&lt;/strong&gt; and although it is not a lot, it is a game that can give surprises despite its simplicity. That estimated half hour is taking into account that the player manages to keep his civilization alive for &lt;strong&gt;at least 20,000 years&lt;/strong&gt;, and in fact it is difficult to do it when there is no defined strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name generator was not as outstanding as other processes in the game, since the construction of syllables repeatedly produces huge blocks of vowels or consonants that cannot be added to a word without making sense of it. Sure, the &lt;strong&gt;alien context&lt;/strong&gt; of the game offers the right environment to ignore linguistic details to a certain extent, but it would be &lt;strong&gt;much more comfortable for the player&lt;/strong&gt; to be able to recognize their cities by a name that they can at least pronounce. I promise I will fix it, don’t lose faith in me, anonymous reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning you can put a seed corresponding to the point from which your initial tribe will originate, &lt;strong&gt;the initial point HAS to be on a beach&lt;/strong&gt;. Each new settlement that is put on the map must be connected to a nearby station, each station will increase its rank as it connects more and more stations to itself. After managing to create 5 metropolis, the game will give more seeds to originate new clans without the need to be connected to other nearby points (this new clans must be used on a beach, far from all other settlements).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CLICK :&lt;/strong&gt; create a new settlement on the map.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K :&lt;/strong&gt; (While hovering the mouse over a settlement) Inflicts damage on the settlement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A :&lt;/strong&gt; Activates auto-exploration. While active random settlements are created near existing ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;V :&lt;/strong&gt; Activates the virus. Random cities will suffer damage while active.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;indicators&quot;&gt;Indicators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROFIT &lt;em&gt;(Colored vertical bar)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; : Index of wealth in your empire. High Profit means good economical times, negative profit means austerity and may lead to famine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seeds :&lt;/strong&gt; How many seeds to start new clans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Map :&lt;/strong&gt; Which map configuration are you watching.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Difficulty :&lt;/strong&gt; Map difficulty, a good start is around 60%;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Growth :&lt;/strong&gt; Grow rate of your civilization.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Population :&lt;/strong&gt; Total number of citizens in your empire.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fuel Production :&lt;/strong&gt; Total fuel points production per year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food Production :&lt;/strong&gt; Total food points production per year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consume :&lt;/strong&gt; Total consume per year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Active/Total :&lt;/strong&gt; Active cities versus total cities placed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lost Legacy :&lt;/strong&gt; Lost cultural content. Time between your first settlement and your oldest active city.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oldest city :&lt;/strong&gt; Oldest active city.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Origin :&lt;/strong&gt;Age of the fist placed city. Years since the beginning of the game.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;line-content&quot; style=&quot;width:30%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type :&lt;/strong&gt; Type of settlement according to size and advancement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Age :&lt;/strong&gt; Age of the settlement in years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pop. :&lt;/strong&gt; Population of the settlement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rank :&lt;/strong&gt; Importance of the city. Relevant to evolve cities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clan :&lt;/strong&gt; Name of the clan that owns the city.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rate :&lt;/strong&gt; Score assigned according to city relevance in the empire.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Savings :&lt;/strong&gt; Amount of goods saved.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Era :&lt;/strong&gt; Period of time in which the empire faces an specific affair.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips&quot;&gt;Tips&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The connectivity range of the stations changes according to their type: larger cities, larger ranges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During golden times you are able to build on water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The savings will increase faster if your profit is high&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While building on water, deeper oceanic floor implies higher consume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Towns built in mountains may have a higher consume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Era changes each 4000 years approximately.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Final score depends on empire expansion, legacy and profit history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/sketches/imferye/imferye.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
PLAY GAME
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 21  / may / 2019&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 04:03:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/03/23/imferye-the-game.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/03/23/imferye-the-game.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>game</category>
        
        <category>random</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Coronavirus media propagation: Twitter NLP</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;outbreak-of-novel-coronavirus-2019-ncov--covid-19&quot;&gt;Outbreak of Novel Coronavirus (2019-nCoV / COVID 19)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The year 2020 started with a lot of bad news, including the high political tension between the US and Iran, the monstrous fires that threaten a considerable part of Australia and its fauna, and the topic that I will talk about today. : The spread of the new coronavirus. To make a brief introduction to what this new virus means, I quote some official sources that can better explain the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;2019 Novel Coronavirus (2019-nCoV) is a virus (more specifically, a coronavirus) identified as the cause of an outbreak of respiratory illness first detected in Wuhan, China on 31 December 2019 . Early on, many of the patients in the outbreak in Wuhan, China reportedly had some link to a large seafood and animal market, suggesting animal-to-person spread. However, a growing number of patients reportedly have not had exposure to animal markets, indicating person-to-person spread is occurring. At this time, it’s unclear how easily or sustainably this virus is spreading between people […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/about/index.html&quot;&gt;Centres for Disease Control and Prevention&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Coronaviruses (CoV) are a large family of viruses that cause illness ranging from the common cold to more severe diseases such as Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS-CoV) and Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS-CoV). A novel coronavirus (nCoV) is a new strain that has not been previously identified in humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Coronaviruses are zoonotic, meaning they are transmitted between animals and people. Detailed investigations found that SARS-CoV was transmitted from civet cats to humans and MERS-CoV from dromedary camels to humans. Several known coronaviruses are circulating in animals that have not yet infected humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Common signs of infection include respiratory symptoms, fever, cough, shortness of breath and breathing difficulties. In more severe cases, infection can cause pneumonia, severe acute respiratory syndrome, kidney failure and even death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Standard recommendations to prevent infection spread include regular hand washing, covering mouth and nose when coughing and sneezing, thoroughly cooking meat and eggs. Avoid close contact with anyone showing symptoms of respiratory illness such as coughing and sneezing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/health-topics/coronavirus&quot;&gt;World Health Organization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-this-study&quot;&gt;About this study&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twitter-as-a-global-agent&quot;&gt;Twitter as a Global agent&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is a social network known to almost everyone since, in addition to being a social network with hundreds of millions of users worldwide, it is a of mass dissemination tool for topics as current affairs, news, politics, science, and culture among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Twitter is a social networking and microblogging service that allows users to post real time messages, called tweets. Tweets are short messages, restricted to 140 characters in length. Due to the nature of this microblogging service (quick and short messages), people use acronyms, make spelling mistakes, use emoticons and other characters that express special meanings […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/W11-0705.pdf&quot;&gt;Sentiment Analysis of Twitter Data&lt;/a&gt;. Agarwal A. ,Xie B., et al.(2011)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to mention that, for a premature humanity that is learning the power of the Internet, the concept of Twitter is experimental: Express an idea with limited characters and make it available to all the people of the world, literally, if desired. As a social experiment of mass distribution of opinions, Twitter takes the lead in exposing the true face of the Internet and its use as a collective intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] Individually, most Twitter messages are stupefyingly trivial. But the true value of Twitter — and the similarly mundane Dodgeball, a tool for reporting your real-time location to friends — is cumulative. The power is in the surprising effects that come from receiving thousands of pings from your posse. And this, as it turns out, suggests where the Web is heading&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/2007/06/st-thompson-4/&quot;&gt;Wired&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sentiment-analysis-applications&quot;&gt;Sentiment Analysis Applications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural language processing is, in other terms, an area of ​​study in the development of Artificial Intelligence that tells us about the way in which computers can interpret human language, creating rules between words and characters in order to assign them some syntactic value. In quantifying these properties, it is easy to notice patterns of association between nearby words, very frequent words or the position in which a word is found within a sentence. These patterns are of great value to go one step further in the interpretation of language: meaning. If a machine is taught to relate these patterns to any quantity that quantifies some dimension of human feeling, it will be easy to make semasiological associations since in many cases they are evident. For example, in terms like or dislike for reviews made to products, relationships such as the given score and the appearance of the words “bad” and “excellent” are usually found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;study-on-twitter-opinions-about-coronavirus&quot;&gt;Study on Twitter Opinions about Coronavirus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day at work, I started to hear the conversation of two colleagues talking about this new disease caused by coronavirus and I thought: everyone is talking about how the coronavirus is rapidly expanding around the world, but very few actually wonder how it is that They got to talk about the coronavirus in the first place. It would be an interesting proposal to see the coronavirus, a threat of global stature, as a social phenomenon exposed to the globalization of the opinion generated by the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this study, the source of information will be Twitter, as a way to reflect the world’s opinion on a subject of great impact such as the Coronavirus. The idea is to draw relevant conclusions about how the world sees this new threat using Sentiment Analysis on Tweets and comparing associated quantities such as the number of likes, retweets and responses. Twitter data is public and extracted using Web Scrappers in Python, they are filtered according to their quality and relevance and then processed by sentiment analysis libraries to quantify properties such as subjectivity and polarity (Positive or negative inclination of Tweet) .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under no circumstances are attempts to plagiarize the work of the sources cited or provide false information. The filter stage of the Tweets is still in development and the poor quality of the information may alter the result slightly, to which the study will be constantly updated to provide more accurate and updated information. Any suggestions on how to improve the study are welcome in my e-mail: davidpaipa03@gmail.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason I can not extract more than one cap of tweets per day, it is probably a restriction that Twitter has to restrict the use of bots on its platform. In any case, I will try to expose the properties of interest in the best possible way, understanding that a limited population is available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;observing-twitter-data&quot;&gt;Observing Twitter Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a preliminary exploration of the data, the appearance of the subject is observed as a global trend from the first day of the year 2020. But beyond the frequency with which the tweets appear, the analysis of sentiment throws relevant data on the nature of the tweets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;word-frequency&quot;&gt;Word Frequency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An analysis of the tweets is executed: initeligible words, grammatical connectors and other filler words are discarded leaving the really important words as a source of information. The effective range is limited to words associated with English, as well as the character dictionary is limited to those alphanumeric in Latin alphabet. Below is a graphic representation of the most frequent words found in the Tweets sample, taking into account that a higher frequency implies greater relevance in the word cloud:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1nWctxStlP2IXLgmjJ8VkRASr8nAHpQV-&quot; alt=&quot;Word Cloud&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The illustration speaks for itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hashtag-frequency&quot;&gt;Hashtag Frequency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the hashtgas used by people, those used in the least relevant tweets are discarded, likewise, only those that make any sense within the context of the coronavirus are preserved. It is expected that the most used hashtag is #coronavirus, but then the other hastags found within the sample are exposed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1g43NsHSaESCXvhP8nqnhAd6FB6tsFm_3&quot; alt=&quot;hastag frequency pieplot&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to mention (as you may have suspected) that these are not all of the hashtags retrieved, but are the most relevant (or most frequent) since many of them appeared one time or where written with terrible ortography. The other ignored hashtags correspond to a 12.5% of the total sample, #coronavirus correspond to a 37.2% and the other 50.3% corresponds to the ones here displayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;polarity&quot;&gt;Polarity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The polarity analysis is a score that shows the positive and negative effects of keywords within a sentence. The keyword analysis is pre-trained with movie reviews obtained from opinion forums to establish a relationship between common words in the expression of an opinion and the feeling generated. This allows you to classify the Tweets given the words they contain in order to determine a feeling or polarity for each one. Depending on this polarity value, the tweet is classified as “Good” or “Bad” if it has a strong feeling inclined to either of these two polarities. If the feeling is not relevant, it is classified as “not interesting.” Below is how the tweets behaved for a population of approximately 600 users per day who talked about the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=10rw4qPnp5_Mi6du8jXw2NPobaEic7DYk&quot; alt=&quot;count histogram&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impact-and-resonance&quot;&gt;Impact and Resonance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Resonance analysis is obtained by quantifying the people reached by each tweet. Measuring this effective population reached, Amplifying the polarity according to the Tweet’s objectivity lead to a value called Impact, which talks about the positive or negative impact of the topic in social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tweet may reach few people, but with an objective approach and a great polarity value it may create a considerable impact. By the other hand, a tweet may reach many people, but if its a subjective Tweet with few sentiment it might not create a great social echo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1EEspInrOaZ0fE__1J3-J4fyqVGi9p1qy&quot; alt=&quot;Resonance plot&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take into account that from the action of 600 users a day a reach of almost 120 thousand individuals was achieved. “Coronavirus” is a concept that spreads from public opinion, knowing that this study was conducted without taking into account publications made by official news sources or any scientific source of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;propagation-and-resistance&quot;&gt;Propagation and Resistance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are going to quantify the average number of people reached by tweet for each day. This amount is calculated by taking out the resonance rate achieved by tweets made on the same day, thus obtaining a number greater than or equal to one corresponding to the number of possible replicas achieved on average for each tweet made on the subject; This number is the propagation index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another number of interest is to quantify how many tweets are left behind given their low subjectivity and neutral polarity. Any Tweet of low impact is considered discarded by the social trend movement and its rate with respect to the amount of daily tweets is called the resistance index. This number between zero and one expresses the proportion of tweets that have to be lost from one day to another given their low interest rate. The following shows how these indices behave over time and a trend line associated with their behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1x7Jw9_1MffmQ_KJ6DHaog1tIJFBOIVhl&quot; alt=&quot;Resonance plot&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;subjectivity-analysis&quot;&gt;Subjectivity Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sentiment analysis model recognizes keywords to determine the degree of subjectivity of a statement. This applied to the tweets quantifies how close they are to be a fact or an opinion according to the vocabulary used in their writing. To determine the propagation of opinions and facts, the proportion of subjective tweets, resistance and resonance by date is taken into account. With this, there is a value corresponding to the volume of tweets with transcendence (echo) classified as fact or opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1Eu4VBCw8jUp2jcn13lT3PEIbWi1RN_V0&quot; alt=&quot;Opinion plot&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By increasing the daily rate of objective tweets using the propagation index and accumulating this value by dates given the persistence in the network of tweets, a new amount arises corresponding to the propagation of objectivity and subjectivity. These amounts correspond to the potential per day of each tweet to generate responses in each of these categories according to objectivity; it is measured in the same units as resonance, as it is also a metric for spreding. Focusing specifically on opinions, one can quantify how many opinions are propagated by each equally propagated fact: this rate is the subjectivity persistence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=19hRbjw7NC7BRWgD-Ea5RkA0wlv-DWY6x&quot; alt=&quot;Information loss plot&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 20:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/coronavirus-twitter-analysis/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/coronavirus-twitter-analysis/</guid>
        
        <category>space</category>
        
        <category>python</category>
        
        <category>nlp</category>
        
        <category>machine</category>
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
        <category>deep</category>
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
        
        <category>topic</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Eigenvalue of myself</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;success&lt;/strong&gt; in facing the daily dilemmas and the occasional unexpected catastrophes that &lt;strong&gt;chance&lt;/strong&gt; places in our path depends on our ability to focus our &lt;strong&gt;superior intellect&lt;/strong&gt; on the study of our &lt;strong&gt;own being&lt;/strong&gt;. Embracing many points of view of the self is a masterful tool for &lt;strong&gt;forging&lt;/strong&gt; any new link with the world. The understanding of being is a practice that the 21st century has put aside despite being in these moments of &lt;strong&gt;cultural mishmash&lt;/strong&gt; when we most need to look within ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anyone who remains with a single perspective of the world is condemned to wander it on one only path.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technique&quot;&gt;Technique&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manual filter of facial transformation as the main template. The other layers are made up of patterns &lt;strong&gt;added by collage&lt;/strong&gt; and Deep Dream patterns added by contrast. The final image was processed &lt;strong&gt;multiple times&lt;/strong&gt; by low-enhancing convolutional filters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-artist&quot;&gt;From the artist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be said to be my version of a &lt;em&gt;“self-portrait”&lt;/em&gt;. A purely subjective representation of what I observed when analyzing my position in the world. I like to represent myself with multiple eyes because I associate them with &lt;strong&gt;knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;the occult&lt;/strong&gt;. For the latter’s purposes, I also often include in many of my pieces patterns with sacred geometry and ancestral symbology, as well as &lt;strong&gt;semasiological links&lt;/strong&gt; between the myths of tarot, religion and divine science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;models-and-references&quot;&gt;Models and references&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;models&quot;&gt;Models&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Myself - Paipa Psyche (David Paipa)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 07:26:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/image/2020/02/12/eigenvalue-of-myself.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/image/2020/02/12/eigenvalue-of-myself.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>image</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
