<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Penrose Trip</title>
    <description>This website is an interactive portal for informative use, which seeks to open a space for the juxtaposition between psychedelia, science, programming and art.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 00:43:35 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 00:43:35 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drawing With Fourier Series</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Profound study of nature is the most fertile source of mathematical discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jean Baptiste Joseph Fourier&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sketch is a didactic representation of what &lt;strong&gt;Fourier series&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;Discrete Fourier Transform (DFT)&lt;/strong&gt; represent when decomposing data into frequencies.The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discrete_Fourier_transform#Definition&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;definition&lt;/a&gt; of the DFT is given by a function that takes in &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; data points \(X_n\) and create &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; new &lt;em&gt;complex numbers&lt;/em&gt; \(\tilde{X}_k\). This resulting coefficients encode data of frequency, phase and amplitude for the decomposed signal. But what does this mean? Well, let me explain briefly the &lt;strong&gt;GENIALITY&lt;/strong&gt; of Fourier’s proposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model works under the hypothesis that &lt;strong&gt;any signal can be decomposed in a summation of sine and cosine waves&lt;/strong&gt;, with different frequencies and amplitudes. A useful analogy is to think of the ripples in the sea as the result of big slow waves caused by the tide, median waves (quicker this time) caused by nearby boats, and small ripples caused by breeze and the fishes under the surface. If we know the magnitude (Amplitude) of each one of these sources, their speed (Frequency) and where they are originated (Phase), we can deduce the state of the sea &lt;em&gt;in any given point&lt;/em&gt;. With a signal is the same: we assume that it is a sum of many cosine and sine waves of different frequencies and magnitudes, and that these coefficients (Frequency, magnitude and phase) can be inferred from the original signal. &lt;strong&gt;This is crazy!&lt;/strong&gt; In the analogy of the sea, this is the equivalent of observing the waves for a finite period of time and, based on the observation, being able to tell the characteristics of &lt;strong&gt;every source&lt;/strong&gt; of movement affecting the sea, from the tide caused by the moon to the tiny perturbations caused by the wind. This is the magic of the &lt;strong&gt;Fourier Series!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discrete_Fourier_transform#Inverse_transform&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;defined&lt;/a&gt; an  &lt;strong&gt;Inverse Discrete Fourier Transform (IDFT)&lt;/strong&gt; which takes the \(\tilde{X}_k\) values and return the \(X_n\) points of the original signal. An important remark is that while the original signal data is in the &lt;strong&gt;time space&lt;/strong&gt; (data points with different intensities distributed in time) the DFT-generated points are in the &lt;strong&gt;frequency space&lt;/strong&gt; and they represent a &lt;strong&gt;fundamental frequency&lt;/strong&gt; of the system for &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; the duration of the signal. This means that each Fourier Coefficient \(\tilde{X}_k\) depends on every data point \(X_n\) and viceversa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, with a known set of frequencies and amplitudes, you can certainly tell more about the signal you have. With this information you can tell which are the &lt;strong&gt;main frequencies&lt;/strong&gt; of the signal and how relevant each of these frequencies are. This is useful, for example, when you want to extract &lt;strong&gt;periodic behaviors in financial data&lt;/strong&gt; or extracting which frequencies are relevant and which are associated with &lt;strong&gt;noise&lt;/strong&gt;. In this last case identifying noise, if you take the frequencies with the smallest intensities (frequencies that are not that relevant: noise) and &lt;strong&gt;set their amplitudes to Zero&lt;/strong&gt; (in the frequency space), when doing the IDFT to the modified \(\tilde{X}_k\) you obtain a the original signal with &lt;strong&gt;suppressed noise&lt;/strong&gt;. You can suppress or amplify frequencies as you wish in the frequency space by tunning amplitudes, so that when the Transformation is reversed the signal is modified as requested. This is a basic principle of DFT that is commonly used when cleaning noise from signals and modifying sound data with tools such as &lt;strong&gt;autotune&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;bass amplifers&lt;/strong&gt; (which amplify low frequencies).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim is to develop a better intuition on what all these summations and complex coefficients mean when reconstructing a discrete succession of points distributed in time (a signal) from frequency information. When learning about the Fourier transform (and Series) sometimes is difficult to picture how a complex exponential can be used as a &lt;em&gt;magic wand&lt;/em&gt; to extract the frequencies of a signal and what this tells us about the signal itself. Off course there are many good teachers and classic examples one can learn form, but I think a good way to learn is to play around with the concept and learn by yourself the consequences of changing every little thing in the model. I created this sketch to learn better the implications of DFT and to show the amazing concept it hides in a simple complex equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing the transformation of a signal is not that &lt;em&gt;magical&lt;/em&gt; in a computer: inserting a set of numbers and extracting other set of numbers is not a remarkable concept for a learner. But a concept that escapes to the mind when having a set of sines and cosines are that they can be related to the rotation of a circle. Furthermore, when using the DFT we are dealing with frequencies, amplitudes and phases, and these can be translated (using trigonometry) to the state of a point going around a circle of specific size (Amplitude) at an specific speed (frequency) and starting in an specific angle (phase). Using this two powerful ideas, DFT and complex exponentials as spinning vectors, is that this sketch is made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program allows you to make a drawing  (a continuous line in 2D) and this can be translated as a set of points with coordinates (x,y). This set of points can also be seen as two different 1D signals, one for X and one for Y, which is convenient since each 1D signal can be analyzed through DFT. When concluding the Transformations we are left with two DFT points in the frequency space ,one for X and one for Y. Now, since &lt;strong&gt;the signal is a summation of the effects of each fundamental frequency&lt;/strong&gt; (each one associated with a \(\tilde{X}_k\)) and each one of these can be expressed as a spinning vector, &lt;strong&gt;we can express X as a sum of vectors spinning with different amplitudes and frequencies&lt;/strong&gt;, each one starting where the previous vector finished (the same goes for Y). The &lt;strong&gt;initial&lt;/strong&gt; angle at which each vector starts spinning &lt;strong&gt;is given by the phase&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total signal is a consequence of all frequencies summed, so &lt;strong&gt;it doesn’t matter the order&lt;/strong&gt; in which they are added (the order in which the vectors are stacked) &lt;strong&gt;as long as they are all taken into account&lt;/strong&gt;. A useful way to order these vector is in &lt;strong&gt;decreasing order of amplitude&lt;/strong&gt;, drawing first the most relevant frequencies (associated with circles of big radius) and the least ones at last (tiny circles). This is useful because if you choose to draw only the first &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; circles (vectors), the signal is going to be pretty similar to the original one but with &lt;strong&gt;less details&lt;/strong&gt;. These details are given by the coefficients of smaller magnitude you chose not to draw. So basically when choosing to draw only the first &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; main frequencies you are creating a &lt;strong&gt;filter&lt;/strong&gt; over the signal, filtering out all the non-relevant details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the sketch you can choose this number &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; and on each axis you can see a plot representation of the main frequencies (the &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; that are drawn) in magnitude (length of the colored bar), phase (blue-red coloring of the bar) and frequency (White dot paired with each bar flashes every time a cycle of that frequency is completed.The faster it flashes, higher the frequency). Each bar is associated with a circle, so that a long bar might be related to a big circle on that axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, draw a figure in the Big left blackboard by &lt;strong&gt;pressing and dragging the left mouse click&lt;/strong&gt;. In order to obtain a good example of Fourier decomposition it is &lt;strong&gt;important&lt;/strong&gt; that the drawing is a &lt;abbr title=&quot;the drawing is a continuous line that finishes where it started&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;closed figure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt;, with no interruptions and ideally drawn slowly so the drawing has enough data points. Drawing fast may give few data points and generate sudden changes in direction, which is an interesting study case too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once your drawing is done, press &lt;strong&gt;Save Board&lt;/strong&gt; in order to store your drawing in memory (Upper smaller board) and then &lt;strong&gt;Transform&lt;/strong&gt; to generate the Fourier decomposition. If you don’t like what is in the blackboard you can press &lt;strong&gt;Blank Board&lt;/strong&gt; to delete the points in the left blackboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the Fourier decomposition is done, you can &lt;strong&gt;control the number of principal frequencies&lt;/strong&gt;  used in the drawing with the &lt;strong&gt;slider&lt;/strong&gt; under the left blackboard. If you want the machine to start drawing again from the beginning you can press &lt;strong&gt;Reset Drawing&lt;/strong&gt; to reset the machine (with your drawing still in memory).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mobile&quot;&gt;Mobile&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version may not work in mobile devices. But if it does, the controls are the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/sketches/fourier2D/fourierDrawing.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
TEST SKETCH
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 15  / mar / 2021&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 02:23:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sketch/2021/02/16/drawing-with-fourier-series.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sketch/2021/02/16/drawing-with-fourier-series.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>visual</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>math</category>
        
        <category>physics</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Scatering Simulation</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Scattering, in physics, is a change in the &lt;em&gt;direction of motion&lt;/em&gt; of a particle because of a &lt;strong&gt;collision&lt;/strong&gt; with another particle.[…] In probing the interior of the atom, the physicist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernest_Rutherford&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ernest Rutherford&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; passed a stream of alpha particles through a thin sheet of gold foil. The alpha particles were emitted by a radioactive material and had enough energy to penetrate an atom; although most passed right through the gold foil, some were &lt;em&gt;deflected&lt;/em&gt; in a way that indicated that the scattering was produced by a &lt;strong&gt;Coulomb force&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/science/scattering&quot;&gt;Britannica Encyclopedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particles with mass and charge are created that are subject to a simulation of N bodies where the only given interaction is the coulomb force (Electrostatic). This implies that the force between particles is proportional to the inverse of the square of the distance, and it is also proportional to the charges of the two interacting bodies. Likewise, two charges of opposite sign have attractive force while two charges of similar sign are subject to a repulsive force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the behavior of particles that obey Coulomb’s laws in 2D had been simulated, the next step was to formulate an &lt;strong&gt;experiment&lt;/strong&gt; that would allow us to see the benefits of said simulation. Particle scattering is a great example to study as it allows us to visualize how &lt;em&gt;small changes&lt;/em&gt; in the charges or positions of the particles on the bombarded surface affect the direction of the &lt;em&gt;incident particle beam&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simulation consistent with expectations is obtained, at least in terms of the defection of charged particles. This is seen when the &lt;strong&gt;dust&lt;/strong&gt; particles (those that make up the incident beam) are repelled or attracted towards the &lt;strong&gt;ions&lt;/strong&gt; (particles with a greater charge that take on red or blue colors depending on the sign of said charge) consistently with their distance to said charges. In ion structures, such as those present in the simulation, we can observe how discrete changes in ions distant from the &lt;strong&gt;point of collision&lt;/strong&gt; of the beam, manage to deflect it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting result is to &lt;em&gt;liberate&lt;/em&gt; an ion from the fixed position where it is inside the structure, leaving it as another free particle within the simulation. Most of the times, this ion is &lt;em&gt;trapped&lt;/em&gt; within the structure in a periodic motion that creates binary oscillations in the deflected beam. These vibrations of the trapped ion manage to create the equivalent of a spectrum in the detector (if any) and only measuring the deflected beam could give indications of these vibrating ions within the structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another result associated with the previous one is associated with the dust particles outside the beam and the &lt;em&gt;inflection points&lt;/em&gt;. When the beam passes very close to an ion, it curves the beam considerably, this is expected given the correlation between force and distance in &lt;strong&gt;coulomb’s laws&lt;/strong&gt;. I call these events &lt;strong&gt;inflection points&lt;/strong&gt;. The interesting thing is that when a particle outside the incident beam disturbs the beam near these points, it manages to create &lt;strong&gt;large disturbances&lt;/strong&gt; compared to a particle that disturbs the beam at any other point in its trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The particle beam enters the screen from the left side. Then it comes across 3 barriers of &lt;em&gt;“ions”&lt;/em&gt;, each with a different charge than the previous layer, and then an &lt;em&gt;object&lt;/em&gt; with ions of arbitrary charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CLICK on an atom to &lt;em&gt;flip&lt;/em&gt; its charge. CLICK on an empty space to create a dust particle (same kind of particle present in the incident beam) with velocity to the left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P (while hovering an ion):&lt;/strong&gt; liberates the ion from its fixed position.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F :&lt;/strong&gt; flips the charge of a random ion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;W :&lt;/strong&gt; Moves the origin of the beam UP.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S :&lt;/strong&gt; Moves the origin of the beam DOWN.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/sketches/scattering/scattering.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
TEST SIMULATION
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 06  / Nov / 2020&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 05:00:01 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/11/06/scattering-simulation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/11/06/scattering-simulation.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>physics</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>simulation</category>
        
        <category>microscopic</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Publication: MNRAS Letters</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;link-to-the-paper&quot;&gt;Link to the paper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Published in &lt;strong&gt;Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society: Letters&lt;/strong&gt; the &lt;em&gt;31 October 2020&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnrasl/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/mnrasl/slaa177/5948101?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;MNRAS Letters&lt;/strong&gt; site publication.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.05160&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt; to arxiv.org site.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2010.05160&quot;&gt;DOWNLOAD PDF&lt;/a&gt; form  arxiv.org&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;co-autor-of-a-publication&quot;&gt;Co-autor of a publication!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally!&lt;/strong&gt; the work of my undergraduate thesis contributed to the study of the formation of &lt;strong&gt;superclusters in cosmological simulations&lt;/strong&gt;. In recent days my thesis advisor together with another undergraduate student wrote a paper where they consolidate the work of some students, including me, in the study of galactic superclusters and their formation in contemporary cosmological simulations (large simulations of structure formation in the universe ) that take into account the cosmology in which we believe our universe unfolds: The &lt;strong&gt;lambda-CDM cosmology&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-in-the-paper&quot;&gt;what’s in the paper?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Superclusters are a convenient way to partition and characterize the large scale structure of the Universe. In this Letter we explore the advantages of defining superclusters as watershed basins in the divergence velocity field. We apply this definition on diverse datasets generated from linear theory and N-body simulations, with different grid sizes, smoothing scales and types of tracers. From this framework emerges a linear scaling relation between the average supercluster size and the autocorrelation length in the divergence field, a result that holds for one order of magnitude from 10 Mpc/h up to 100 Mpc/h. These results suggest that the divergence-based definition provides a robust context to quantitatively compare results across different observational or computational frameworks. Through its connection with linear theory, it can also facilitate the exploration of how supercluster properties depend on cosmological parameters, paving the way to use superclusters as cosmological probes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paper’s abstract&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-thesis&quot;&gt;My thesis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PaipaPsyche/SuperClusterCharacterization/blob/master/FinalDocument.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;undergraduate thesis work&lt;/a&gt; was focused on studying the &lt;strong&gt;statistical relevance&lt;/strong&gt; of superclusters with  characteristics similar to the ones observed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1409.0880&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tully et al.&lt;/a&gt; in our local supercluster &lt;strong&gt;Laniakea&lt;/strong&gt;. This was made by comparing these characteristics with the ones observed in supercluster formation in cosmological simulations. My method consisted on first identifying the supercluster formation using &lt;strong&gt;velocity divergence fields&lt;/strong&gt; and later, using the watershed algorithm, making a segmentation of the simulated space in superclusters. Over the observed superclusters I analyzed properties such as &lt;strong&gt;density, mass, volume and shape&lt;/strong&gt; arriving to the conclusion that obtaining a supercluster similar to Laniakea was an event of &lt;strong&gt;very low probability&lt;/strong&gt;, implying that &lt;strong&gt;Laniakea is atypical&lt;/strong&gt; in the context of cosmological simulations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 02:15:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/MNRAS-publication-superclusters/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/MNRAS-publication-superclusters/</guid>
        
        <category>information</category>
        
        <category>physics</category>
        
        
        <category>information</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cellular Battle Royale</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With more experience with genetic algorithms, I decided to experiment with one that involved continuous and more complex behaviors. In my other genetic learning sketches, the genetic algorithm always boils down to a set of discrete values as a possible gene expression, but in this case a much broader spectrum of values and possible alterations is being taken. They are independent cells that react to three external agents: waste, food and other cells. The cells roam in a free space and their genetic expression regulates everything within, from nutrition to movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I have been interested in establishing points of comparison between the &lt;strong&gt;perfect chaos&lt;/strong&gt; of nature and the &lt;strong&gt;determinism&lt;/strong&gt; of computing. Addressing complex concepts such as &lt;em&gt;‘evolution’&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;‘learning’&lt;/em&gt; with this type of exercise leaves an appetizer for all the mysteries that lie beyond logic and biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Playing to be God is not that bad … I mean, what could go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The genetic monitor allows to graph the genetic expression of the cell in such a way that it is easy to determine the origin of its affinity to certain behaviors. The cell monitor allows you to track all the vital signs and content of the cell it represents. Both are ways to visualize confusing data in a more attractive and intuitive way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each Genetic code has a unique number to identify itself. Each  code has two parents, each with an &lt;strong&gt;ID number&lt;/strong&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;centered-square&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;imgsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/sketch-royale-img1.png&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;txtsq&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;imglbl&quot;&gt;

      Genetic Code and Vital Signs of an arbitrary cell.

    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genetic-slot-monitor&quot;&gt;Genetic Slot Monitor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the representation of the genetic code of each cell. This might be useful when comparing different genomes and verifying inheritance properties. You can detail some graphic properties that provide information about genetic expression (left box of the image):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;numbers&quot;&gt;Numbers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the lower left corner there is the generation of the given genome.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the bottom,centered, the name of the genetic id code in format “DAD-ME-MOM”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When selected in the genetic Slot Monitor, the boxes have the slot number in the top left corner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;central-core&quot;&gt;Central Core&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the middle of the diagram there is a circle that represents the &lt;strong&gt;sensitivity&lt;/strong&gt;  gene of the cell. The larger the circle, the cell has a greater detection range for food, debris and other cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;metabolic rate&lt;/strong&gt; gene of the cell is represented as the speed of the internal clock of this circle. A cell with a slow metabolic rate looks like a slow clock, implying that this cell takes much longer to complete internal processes and make decisions. This metabolic rate can best be compared using a white circular arc that is within the main circle, the length of this arc represents the time between cycles of the cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;top--axis&quot;&gt;Top  axis&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;strong&gt;affinity&lt;/strong&gt; axis, where a line extending to the left means a negative value and a line to the right means positive affinity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Green gene is the &lt;strong&gt;cell affinity&lt;/strong&gt;, meaning the &lt;em&gt;attraction&lt;/em&gt; to other cells. the extra line segment represent a bias in the mass subtraction in order to react to the other cell’s size.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Blue gene is the &lt;strong&gt;food affinity&lt;/strong&gt;, meaning attraction to food particles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Red gene is the &lt;strong&gt;waste affinity&lt;/strong&gt;, meaning attraction to waste particles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bottom--axis&quot;&gt;Bottom  axis&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;strong&gt;deterministic&lt;/strong&gt; axis, where a line extending to the left means a deterministic cell behavior and a line to the right means random movement approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The top olive gene is the &lt;strong&gt;speed persistence&lt;/strong&gt;, which each cycle determines whether being conservative and keeping the same direction (Right) or changing the movement direction according to other internal and external responses (Left)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The bottom purple gene is the &lt;strong&gt;arbitrary movement&lt;/strong&gt;, which each cycle determines whether taking  a step in a random direction (Right) or to obey to other internal and external responses (Left)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;left--axis&quot;&gt;Left  axis&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;strong&gt;exploration&lt;/strong&gt; axis. The longer the line corresponding to a process, it means that the cell uses more energy in that process each cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cyan gene is for &lt;strong&gt;shield regeneration&lt;/strong&gt;. High values means high energy investment in cellular wall regeneration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pink gene is for &lt;strong&gt;movement&lt;/strong&gt;. Higher values represent strong thrusts in cell movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;right-axis&quot;&gt;Right axis&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;strong&gt;nutrition&lt;/strong&gt; axis. The longer the line corresponding to a process, it means that the cell uses more energy in that process each cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The yellow gene regulates the &lt;strong&gt;energy converter&lt;/strong&gt;. High values means ingested food is rapidly converted into energy, but high conversion rates consume more energy and generate more wastes as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The orange gene regulates the  &lt;strong&gt;waste output&lt;/strong&gt;. Higher values in cells means they invest more energy in waste disposal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cellular-vital-monitor&quot;&gt;Cellular Vital Monitor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This diagram allows to keep an account of the internal processes of the cell as well as the resources it has and its characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On top, a white loading bar representing the &lt;strong&gt;metabolic rate&lt;/strong&gt; of the cell. Each time the bar is completed, a new cycle begins.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The exterior cyan circle represents the &lt;strong&gt;shield&lt;/strong&gt; integrity. Once it reaches 0, damage will be taken by the cell’s health.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the inner yellow circle is the &lt;strong&gt;energy&lt;/strong&gt; level. Once 0, energy for completing the cycles will be taken from the cell’s health.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The inner green pie plot is the cell’s &lt;strong&gt;health&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The purple number is the cell’s &lt;strong&gt;energy reservoir&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The red number is the &lt;strong&gt;waste&lt;/strong&gt; level inside the cell. Once 100 is reached, each cycle the cell has 100 or more waste it loses health.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The orange number is the number of &lt;strong&gt;unprocessed food&lt;/strong&gt; particles inside the cell.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The bottom left number is the cell’s &lt;strong&gt;mass&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goals-and-indicators&quot;&gt;Goals and Indicators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;main-goal&quot;&gt;MAIN GOAL&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;main goal&lt;/em&gt; is the scoring method for each cell, giving the cells the chance to reproduce in next generation depending on this score. the different scoring methods evaluate different goals, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;eat :&lt;/strong&gt; eat cells and food.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;food :&lt;/strong&gt; eat as much food as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;size :&lt;/strong&gt; gain mass.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cycles :&lt;/strong&gt; complete full cycles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;time :&lt;/strong&gt; survive as long as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;hunting :&lt;/strong&gt; eat other cells.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;berserk :&lt;/strong&gt; eat EVERYTHING.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;die :&lt;/strong&gt; existence is pain. I just want to die fast.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pick :&lt;/strong&gt; eat as much food and cells (relative to waste) as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;poop :&lt;/strong&gt; eat as much waste as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cell-indicators&quot;&gt;CELL INDICATORS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each cell has 4 information slots (2 in the upper edge and 2 in the lower edge) where you can display the information you choose:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;health :&lt;/strong&gt; health level.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;score :&lt;/strong&gt; score (according to main goal selection).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;shield :&lt;/strong&gt; shield integrity level.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;energy :&lt;/strong&gt; energy level.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mass :&lt;/strong&gt; mass index.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;food :&lt;/strong&gt; food particles taken.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dirt :&lt;/strong&gt; waste particles taken.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;preys :&lt;/strong&gt; cells eaten.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cycles :&lt;/strong&gt; cycles completed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;id :&lt;/strong&gt; genetic id.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dad :&lt;/strong&gt; dad’s genetic id.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mom :&lt;/strong&gt; mom’s genetic id.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;none :&lt;/strong&gt; display nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The buttons and sliders of the application allow you to interact with the simulation parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SLIDERS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Viscosity&lt;/strong&gt; defines the resistance the medium has to the movement of cells.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Initial Food&lt;/strong&gt; sets the number of food particles present in the beginning of each generation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minimum food&lt;/strong&gt; is the minimum number of food particles that the simulation has. If there are less food particles, the simulation will append new ones to the medium.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BUTTONS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nex Generation&lt;/strong&gt; polls the population score and resets the map, generating a new genetic pool with the previous generation data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove Items&lt;/strong&gt; removes all food and waste particles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear monitors&lt;/strong&gt; blanks all the genetic slots.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toggle vectors&lt;/strong&gt; switches ON/OFF to display all the cell vectors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enable/Disable auto-experiments&lt;/strong&gt; switches ON/OFF the automatic experimentation procedure. Always press &lt;strong&gt;RESET&lt;/strong&gt; when beginning a new experiment sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RESET&lt;/strong&gt; clear all genetic displays, deletes genetic pool and restarts generation counter. It can only be activated if &lt;em&gt;auto-experiments&lt;/em&gt; are enabled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SELECTORS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main Goal&lt;/strong&gt; defines the scoring method for the cells.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CELL INDICATORS&lt;/strong&gt; set the 4 values that each cell has displayed in the upper and lower margins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KEYBOARD &amp;amp; MOUSE:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CLICK :&lt;/strong&gt; operates buttons,selectors and sliders. click on a cell to display its genetic code and its vital signs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1 / 2 / 3 / 4 (While hovering a cell):&lt;/strong&gt; displays the cell´s genetic code in genetic slot (1,2,3, or 4) .&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N :&lt;/strong&gt; Next generation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates a new cell in the cursor XY position&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates a food particle in the cursor XY position.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;W :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates a Waste particle in the cursor XY position.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;X (While hovering a cell):&lt;/strong&gt; Explodes the cell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/sketches/CellRoyale/cell-royale.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
TEST SKETCH
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 13  / sept / 2020&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2020 03:28:20 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/08/29/cellular-battle-royale.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/08/29/cellular-battle-royale.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>genetic</category>
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Genetic Learning: Smart Rockets</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For me, the level at which natural selection causes the phenomenon of adaptation is the level of the replicator - the gene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Dawkins&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the simulation there are rockets that every certain interval of time are pushed in an arbitrary direction, the objective of these rockets is to reach a target in a specific instant of time. The rockets give a defined number of jumps and must reach the goal just in time, however, they have no information about the position of the target so they must learn how to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simulation runs for generations, and it is expected that with each generation the rockets will become more and more precise in their task of hitting the target on time. The rockets have &lt;em&gt;genes&lt;/em&gt; that encode each of the jumps that the rocket does, then at the end of each generation a score is assigned to each rocket and based on this score the rocket has more or less probability of reproducing its genes in the next generation. The genes are in the form of a 2D vector, since in each jump what happens is that a vector is added to the speed that the rocket already had. At the end of each genetic mix, a certain percentage of mutations is generated in the genes in order to diversify the solutions and prevent the system from remaining in dead ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of rockets as an example of genetic learning is not new, but that does not make it any less interesting. Machine learning can occur in different ways, but reinforcement learning is based more on experimentation and trial-error dynamics. Other learning methods use more direct ways of adapting the model to learn new tasks (sometimes based on other solutions to the problem in order to learn new ones), but the genetic algorithm is responsible for exploring the solution space based on the experience of the system, without external examples of how to fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In proposing the problem, I wanted to find a way to optimize genetic learning, even when this is already a form of optimization. I wanted to explore ways in which the algorithm can be modified to converge faster and avoid classic genetic learning problems in the case of rockets in particular. This is how I got to the implementation of the adaptive response system (AR) and its use to adjust the learning parameters of the simulation automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is surprising. The rockets manage to learn in &lt;strong&gt;most cases&lt;/strong&gt; a route that allows them to complete the task. Some problems stood out when doing a few experiments, but in general the result obtained was satisfactory.
Some of the model highlights are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reproduction-method&quot;&gt;Reproduction method&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evaluation criterion was defined based on the final distance from the rocket to the target, assigning a score from &lt;strong&gt;1 to 1000&lt;/strong&gt;, 1000 being the case where the rocket finished its journey in the center of the target. With this metric, a reproduction criterion was established in order to &lt;strong&gt;prioritize the reproduction of the highest scores&lt;/strong&gt;: a pool of candidates is generated, from which the parents of the future generation will be selected. The pool is initialized empty, and each rocket of the actual generation adds as many copies of itself as its score indicates, that is, a rocket with a score of 800 contributes 800 copies of itself to the pool. Then, for all the &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; rockets needed for the next generation a pair of candidates form the pool are chosen. Their &lt;em&gt;genes&lt;/em&gt; are reproduced using the method mentioned below, and once all &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; genetic sets are generated, the simulation starts over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genetic mixing occurs between pairs of rockets and happens by randomly using the following mixing methods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mean:&lt;/strong&gt; The vectors of both rockets for each jump are averaged, resulting in a set of vectors of the same length&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Switch:&lt;/strong&gt; The resulting rocket takes in each jump vector XY the X form one parent rocket and Y form the other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Split:&lt;/strong&gt; The resulting rocket takes the first &lt;em&gt;j&lt;/em&gt; genes from one parent and the rest from the other parent. &lt;em&gt;j&lt;/em&gt; is chosen at random each time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Random:&lt;/strong&gt; Each gene is chosen randomly from each parent (50/50).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adaptive-response-system-ar&quot;&gt;Adaptive Response System (AR)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the problems that can arise when trying to train genetic algorithms, those that I wanted to deal with with the AR system were two in specific: setting a mutation rate and an effective tolerance range for the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mutation-rate&quot;&gt;Mutation rate&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mutation rate allows to preserve the diversity in the solutions by &lt;strong&gt;introducing random “failures”&lt;/strong&gt; to the genes already generated for the next generation. If this rate is very high, it is impossible for the system to converge to a solution, and if it is very low it is possible that the system normalizes to a false solution without reaching the objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AR system &lt;strong&gt;gradually reduces the mutation rate&lt;/strong&gt; as the average performance of the population increases. This allows that in the first generations there is much variability while when finding a solution, the system reduces the mutation rate in order to converge more quickly in future generations. The magic of this part of the AR is in reducing the probability of mutation as the system approaches an &lt;strong&gt;apparently viable solution&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;likelihood-normalizer&quot;&gt;Likelihood Normalizer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The score is assigned with a function dependent on the distance between the final position of the rocket and the target. This function can be normalized by a number that, when increasing, allows rockets at a greater distance to achieve higher scores. Similarly, reducing this number makes the target’s tolerance area smaller, assigning high scores only to rockets that are really close. This number is called the &lt;strong&gt;Likelihood Normalizer&lt;/strong&gt;. A very large LN allows rockets to gradually find the target when they are far from it, since the score function is visible at a greater distance. When the rockets are close to the target having a large LN is &lt;strong&gt;useless&lt;/strong&gt; as it is more difficult to find noticeable changes in the scoring function with small displacements. On the other hand, when using small LNs it is possible to have better precision to detect the target in the vicinity of the rocket, but consequently it is difficult for rockets that are far away to feel relevant changes in the scoring function to &lt;strong&gt;approach the target&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;issues&quot;&gt;Issues&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system showed that it can learn to find solutions for certain parameters, however there are problems that arise from the same nature of the algorithm and that can be evidenced when trying fairly complex experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The algorithm is good at finding the way to problems with a &lt;strong&gt;single solution&lt;/strong&gt;, however when there are many possible ways the reproduction algorithm generates new candidates that when trying to mix these possible solutions, they obtain a terrible solution. This &lt;strong&gt;slows down the learning algorithm&lt;/strong&gt; for long periods of time as the system converges to just one of the multiple solutions it found.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the number of jumps is very large, the algorithm has many parameters to train and it also usually takes longer. this was expected as each additional jump must be trained as a consequence of the others. But another effect of having many thrusts is that the algorithm may have to find a &lt;strong&gt;less optimal route&lt;/strong&gt; to reach the goal, as it has many displacement opportunities. In this attempt to &lt;strong&gt;compress&lt;/strong&gt; the jumps or &lt;strong&gt;nullify&lt;/strong&gt; the effects of the extra ones, the algorithm comes up with many possible ways that result in a good solution, which brings us to the previous problem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the target is near an edge, rockets that &lt;strong&gt;narrowly miss&lt;/strong&gt; the target when trying to reach it and that could have been good solutions often collide with the edge, &lt;strong&gt;nullifying what could have been a good solution&lt;/strong&gt; only by a very small margin. This is why by default the right border is disabled.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The buttons and sliders of the application allow you to interact with the simulation parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SLIDERS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gravity&lt;/strong&gt; defines a vertical acceleration constant. If Gravity is positive then it pulls downwards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;max. time&lt;/strong&gt; sets the target timer. This defines the time in which rockets have to reach the target.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;# jumps&lt;/strong&gt; sets the number of hops each rocket does. Effective after RESET.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delay&lt;/strong&gt; is the time delay between jumps of the rockets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BUTTONS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generation 1&lt;/strong&gt; sets then generation counter to 1. This might be useful in controlled rigorous experiments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delete obstacles&lt;/strong&gt; removes all obstacles set in the simulation, without affecting anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RESET&lt;/strong&gt; reboots all rockets, reboots the simulation but keeps the parameters set by user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; There are parameters that do not change unless the simulation is restarted (RESET button).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0 / 1 / 2 / 3 / 4  :&lt;/strong&gt; Set scenario.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates an squared obstacle centered in the cursor position.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates a circular obstacle centered in the cursor position.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T :&lt;/strong&gt; Sets the target location in the cursor position.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;O :&lt;/strong&gt; Sets the rocket origin location in the cursor position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/sketches/genetic-rockets/rockets.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
TEST SKETCH
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 08  / aug / 2020&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 07:08:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/08/08/genetic-rockets.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/08/08/genetic-rockets.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>genetic</category>
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SIR Simulation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The peak of the COVID-19 crisis seemed like the perfect opportunity to create an SIR environment to simulate the propagation of an infection within a population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simulation is based on &lt;strong&gt;individual agents&lt;/strong&gt; that walk randomly through the simulation space (Brownian motion), these agents can be in one of 3 possible states: &lt;strong&gt;Susceptible&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Infected&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Recovered&lt;/strong&gt;.
The &lt;strong&gt;(S)usceptible&lt;/strong&gt; agents are those who have not contracted the disease and have the potential to acquire it, within the simulation they are represented with the color white. The &lt;strong&gt;(I)nfected&lt;/strong&gt; are represented with the color red, and they are those who carry the disease and are capable of transmitting it to susceptible agents, this state changes after a few days. Finally, the &lt;strong&gt;(R)ecovered&lt;/strong&gt; agents are those that were infected and, after a certain amount of time, lose their potential to infect and become infected. The latter are reflected in two cases within the simulation: those that die and disappear from the simulation, and those that survive the virus and acquire immunity, turning blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simulation has a set of parameters that can be played with and the important thing is to see &lt;strong&gt;how these changes can affect the spread of a disease&lt;/strong&gt; within a toy population. You can play with attributes of the disease, such as days of incubation or percentage of mortality, as well as possible containment strategies. all within the framework of a fixed population that may (or may not) obey the standards of containment that are established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the current &lt;strong&gt;global emergency situation&lt;/strong&gt;, where a virus threatens to attack the most susceptible, it is important to be aware of how the virus attacks us to know how to respond accordingly. Many governments have opted for &lt;strong&gt;radical health measures&lt;/strong&gt; that have managed to &lt;strong&gt;contain the spread&lt;/strong&gt; of the virus in a remarkable way, but it is also true that some governments also have more ignorant leaders who ignore the situation and in some cases promote misinformation in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems important to me that people can &lt;strong&gt;experiment&lt;/strong&gt; with these types of simulations so that they realize the importance of complying with sanitary measures, such as hand washing and social distancing, and see for themselves &lt;strong&gt;the effects of small daily decisions&lt;/strong&gt;. The problem in these countries with stubborn leaders is that they blindly trust a false promise of security, when a simple simulation like the one I did can show that sanitary measures are, in fact, our &lt;strong&gt;best weapon against a catastrophe&lt;/strong&gt; of such magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simulation responds well to the parameters and the changes made to them. In other words, expected results are obtained by, for example, increasing the contagion rate or introducing restrictive measures, seeing these changes reflected in the &lt;strong&gt;contagion curve&lt;/strong&gt; and the mortality rate.
An added value is the line defined by the &lt;strong&gt;health coverage&lt;/strong&gt; present in the simulation: it is a value defined in favor of &lt;em&gt;“how many infected people can the public health system treat?”&lt;/em&gt;. When this number is exceeded, fatal cases increase considerably, this factor being relevant to determine the lethality of the virus. A simulation where sanitation can only handle a small number of infected usually has many more deaths than one with a higher percentage of coverage. In real life, the number of patients that can be cared for in &lt;em&gt;intensive care units&lt;/em&gt; is a relevant parameter to determine the impact of the virus on the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The buttons of the application allow you to interact with the simulation parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PARAMETERS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ABOUT THE CONTEXT:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dispersion Index&lt;/strong&gt; is the mean speed of the agents moving through the simulation space.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration Rate&lt;/strong&gt; sets the rate of agents that will obey the sanitary measures. The percentage is constant in the simulation, but the agents that disobey change once in a while.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Population&lt;/strong&gt; sets the number of agents in the simulation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medical Coverage&lt;/strong&gt; is the percentage of population that can be in UCIs at the same time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RESET button&lt;/strong&gt; resets the simulation with the parameters that are set at the moment of pressing the button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ABOUT THE DISEASE:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Incubation period&lt;/strong&gt; is the average of day that the infected carry the sickness before recovering or dying.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mortality&lt;/strong&gt; is the probability of dying once infected. This may increase with the exceeding of medical coverage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contagion rate&lt;/strong&gt; determines the probability of getting the disease if a Susceptible spends one whole day with an Infected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ABOUT THE SANITARY RESTRICTIONS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Movement restriction&lt;/strong&gt; sets the obeying agents to be static. Similar to a confinement measure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Washing hands&lt;/strong&gt; reduces the contagion rate in a half.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social distancing&lt;/strong&gt; makes the movement slow and reduces the radius of contagion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Closed experiment&lt;/strong&gt; sets the simulation in a closed box, or one with open borders. When borders are open, all agents that exit one side of the box, enters by the opposite side.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INDICATORS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P(I)&lt;/strong&gt; observed probability of being infected.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Growth&lt;/strong&gt; percentage of the healthy population of last day that got infected today.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P(D)&lt;/strong&gt; observed probability of dying once infected.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AVG-MIR-MI&lt;/strong&gt; AVG is the average contagion rate given the ones already infected until the last day and the total number of agents. The MI is the most number of agents an infected agent has infected directly. The MIR is the MI divided by the number of days this agent was considered infectious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/sketches/sir-simulation/SIR-simulation.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
TEST SKETCH
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 02  / may / 2020&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 07:08:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/08/08/SIR-simulation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sketch/2020/08/08/SIR-simulation.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>simulation</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>B[ORDERS] : Organic behavior in algorithms</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welcome traveler!&lt;/strong&gt; If you have arrived here it is because you are either part of activity B[ORDERS] or you just came across this post by curiosity. In either case, feel welcome to participate and explore the content of the workshop. &lt;strong&gt;Fuzzy Binaires&lt;/strong&gt; is seeking collaboration and community through their own shared practices of open coding, tinkering and making art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;B[ORDERS]* is an online interdisciplinary workshop program running from July 26 to August 2 2020 in which an interdisciplinary group will question the relations between &lt;strong&gt;technology, orders and borders&lt;/strong&gt;. What can be learned from taking positions that refuse the logic of physical and digital borders?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;em&gt;Fuzzy Binaires&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-border&quot;&gt;The Border&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For centuries, the blurred border between the living and the non-living has haunted every corner of the colorful and growing edifice of human knowledge. Since ancient times there have been stories in different religions of how &lt;strong&gt;life arises out of nothing&lt;/strong&gt; by divine will and, in some cases, life itself is forged with inert materials. Today we know that inert materials, such as minerals and molecules, constitute life itself, and that the most specific phenomena depend on their &lt;strong&gt;different configurations&lt;/strong&gt;. This may have been imagined long before the invention of the microscope, but even now it &lt;strong&gt;is difficult to paint a border&lt;/strong&gt; where the inert becomes life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_7wKjTf_RlI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it wasn’t until a few decades ago that we began to understand how &lt;strong&gt;complex&lt;/strong&gt; the microverse and its rules can be. In the 20th century it was discovered that atoms are not perfect clocks as previously believed, but that they are clouds of probability and that, by construction, they build the &lt;strong&gt;strong link&lt;/strong&gt; that exists between the origin of life and the randomness of the quantum world. A completely ordered system cannot give life to life, just as a completely chaotic system cannot maintain it. Creating chaos is simple, but keeping chaos organized and focused is not that easy. I don’t know the definition of life, but many of us can agree that it shares the characteristics of an &lt;strong&gt;unstable, growing and emerging system&lt;/strong&gt; that combines the diversity of chaos with the coherence of self-organization, leading to &lt;strong&gt;aggregate phoenomena&lt;/strong&gt; that increase in complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the workshop I want to make you question what is your definition of this limit, if it exists, and how computing can open our minds to more deterministic perspectives that can also lead to chaos. I want to contrast the phenomena that can be seen in nature with the behaviors observed in the evolution of simple simulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;observing-complexity&quot;&gt;Observing complexity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following case studies, we will approach two recognized algorithms in computing, analyzing them from the perspective of emerging behaviors and experimenting with the infinite possibilities they offer. The exercise is precisely to &lt;strong&gt;explore the endless analogies&lt;/strong&gt; that can be built between the natural world and emerging behaviors, that is why in parts of the talk these systems will be discussed as simple algorithms, and sometimes as if they were an organism or living tissue. We are going to &lt;strong&gt;let the imagination fly&lt;/strong&gt; a bit and let the patterns become visible through our perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;emergent-behaviors&quot;&gt;Emergent behaviors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key points of this workshop is the concept of &lt;strong&gt;emergency&lt;/strong&gt;. This corresponds to all the properties that can be evidenced in a system but that are irreducible to its minimal subsystems. The definition that can be easily found on the internet is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] Emergence occurs when an entity is observed to have properties its parts do not have on their own. These properties or behaviors emerge only when the parts interact in a wider whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of the workshop lies in our ability to visually explore the systems and intuit which behaviors are not explainable as side effects of each part of the system, but a great consequence of the system’s interaction as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;study-cases&quot;&gt;Study cases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of each case study and how it fits the purpose of the activity will be discussed below, however, the most specific content of each sketch is available on the description site of each one (proportional links).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;flocking-ecosystem&quot;&gt;Flocking ecosystem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first algorithm that we are going to analyze is the &lt;strong&gt;flocking algorithm&lt;/strong&gt;. This is characterized by resembling how birds and fish group together in their &lt;strong&gt;movement through a limited space populated by many individuals&lt;/strong&gt;. Although it is an algorithm that has been known for a long time, it is possible to make infinite modifications that undoubtedly make the simulation more interesting, such as the modifications I introduced to do this study. I added agents that create &lt;strong&gt;another level of interaction&lt;/strong&gt; between individuals and lead to the appearance of behaviors analogous to those visible in &lt;strong&gt;ecosystems&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;special-ad&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://penrosetrip.co/sketch/2020/04/13/flocking-ecosystem.html&quot;&gt;
&lt;b style=&quot;font-size:19px&quot;&gt; FLOCKING ECOSYSTEM SIMULATION &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What behaviors can you identify in any region of the simulation that might resemble interaction between species?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you think this is how some mechanism of biology works?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What SIMPLE new behaviors would you introduce in order to diversify behaviors?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2d-cellular-automata&quot;&gt;2D Cellular Automata&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a laboratory created to teach people with little programming context** how to program simple behaviors** in cellular automata. The granularity of the design allows users to create their own rules for interacting on the 2D grid through a minimal and intuitive graphical interface. It’s also a type of system known for decades called a &lt;strong&gt;cellular automaton&lt;/strong&gt;, which consists of a grid of cells that change states based on the state of their neighborhood. Defining these interaction rules in each cell of the grid creates a system of many agents that interact with a high tendency to &lt;strong&gt;chaos and complexity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;special-ad&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://penrosetrip.co/sketch/2020/05/06/2D-cellular-automata-lab.html&quot;&gt;
&lt;b style=&quot;font-size:19px&quot;&gt; 2D CELLULAR AUTOMATA LAB &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;discussion-1&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you generate a tissue of each type shown in the Lab site?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do you think the rules for conway and conway-4 are suitable for complex patterns?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which applications can you see for this type of systems?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science tells us that &lt;strong&gt;complex organized behavior can arise out of complete chaos&lt;/strong&gt;, as seen at the origin of the universe itself that begins with absolute disorder and gives rise to events like life and matter. With a set of indivisible unit elements that follow definite rules, the universe managed to build something as complex as consciousness, and after millennia of experimentation, it produced intelligent entities with curiosity. These &lt;strong&gt;scenarios&lt;/strong&gt; are replicable thanks to modern computing and show macroscopic effects of the interaction between individuals that are difficult to imagine only knowing the initial programming. This leads us to think and ramble on the imaginary border that exists between &lt;strong&gt;programming and biology&lt;/strong&gt;, between science and philosophy, between engineering and contemplation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How did this workshop change your way of seeing everyday phenomena?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Has your definition of the boundary between life and non-life changed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;let-us-know-your-experience&quot;&gt;Let us know your experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you have learned something new with this workshop, let us learn from you too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe name=&quot;embed_readwrite&quot; src=&quot;https://pad.riseup.net/p/B%5BORDERS%5D_-_Organic_algorithms?showControls=true&amp;amp;showChat=true&amp;amp;showLineNumbers=true&amp;amp;useMonospaceFont=false&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/BORDERS/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/BORDERS/</guid>
        
        <category>information</category>
        
        <category>page</category>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>event</category>
        
        <category>art</category>
        
        
        <category>information</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tentaciones y demonios</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The representation of the devil in the Tarot is usually linked to &lt;strong&gt;creativity, desire and carnality&lt;/strong&gt;. Lust and temptation are but facets of an irascible driving force that lies in the &lt;strong&gt;human will&lt;/strong&gt;. Free will is the opportunity that randomness gives us to interact with the cosmos in the way that our desire dictates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;technique&quot;&gt;Technique&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast superposition of more than 20 layers of &lt;strong&gt;convolutional neural network designs&lt;/strong&gt; and recognized paintings in the infernal field of art.
The convolution of most of the layers was done with Deep Dream, a smaller portion was treated with Style Transfer and the other layers were only processed by color shades. The main layer is a photo without prior treatment, so the original features of this can still be differentiated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-artist&quot;&gt;From the artist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model in the picture is a friend of mine whom I have always admired for promoting the culture of temptation. I am referring to the ambit of &lt;strong&gt;reflecting sensuality&lt;/strong&gt; through the mirror and attracting curious glances without involving direct interest. Just as I mentioned before, my intention with the piece is to reflect the &lt;strong&gt;mischief of carnality&lt;/strong&gt; as a side effect of an amazingly &lt;strong&gt;complex mind&lt;/strong&gt;.
I would never consider myself as a model that inspires eroticism, but this does not make me alien to this one. The representation of desire is also an art and although I do not get very close to the conventional representation of lust, the relationship with the figure of the beast is only a mental bridge with the Tarot myth that I wanted to introduce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;models-and-references&quot;&gt;Models and references&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;models&quot;&gt;Models&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kevin Andrade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pictures&quot;&gt;Pictures&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Fall of the damned&lt;/em&gt; - Peter Paul Rubens - &lt;strong&gt;1620&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Defeat of Sennacherib&lt;/em&gt; - Peter Paul Rubens - &lt;strong&gt;1612&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Death of Sardanapalus&lt;/em&gt; - Eugene Delacroix&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;signorcasaubon&lt;/em&gt; - Marten de Vos-Hell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 01:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/image/2020/06/11/tentaciones-y-demonios.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/image/2020/06/11/tentaciones-y-demonios.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>image</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Penrose Trip: A whole new universe</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Penrose Trip&lt;/strong&gt; is a non-profit site whose purpose is to leave &lt;em&gt;interesting questions&lt;/em&gt; loose on the streets of the modern world with the only hope of generating even more doubts. The aim is to touch sensitive fibers regarding the compartmentalization of human thought, since the definition of the line between art and science is challenged. Of course, the strong &lt;strong&gt;psychedelic component&lt;/strong&gt; of this project cannot be ignored, and it is in this context of perpetual hallucination that the aesthetics of artificial intelligence and randomness make sense; in a world &lt;strong&gt;out of focus&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goodbye-old-penrose&quot;&gt;Goodbye, old Penrose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project has been carried out only by me since the creation of the page in the free hosting services of Github in 2018. The page’s first approach was as an image gallery, but with the time it became a gallery of my work and, therefore, an interactive portfolio. It had been carried out with simple HTML pages, with poor Javascript and CSS, and to be honest it was not so pretty aesthetically. This was acceptable as long as it was a portal for personal use, but now that it is more open to the public and even serving as a teaching tool for some Hackathon events, it can only mean one thing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;special-ad&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;

&lt;b style=&quot;font-size:19px&quot;&gt; It is time to migrate to a whole new universe &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-migrate&quot;&gt;How to migrate?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;well, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jekyll is a static site generator. You give it text written in your favorite markup language and it uses layouts to create a static website. You can tweak how you want the site URLs to look, what data gets displayed on the site, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-Jekyll Website&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll allows a simple implementation for static pages that allows to segregate posts (like this one) by themes, tags, etc. It is a simple and efficient way to migrate &lt;strong&gt;Penrose Trip&lt;/strong&gt; with enough requirements for online execution and storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-future&quot;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been almost 3 weeks since the migration started and I’m still getting warm. Much of this time has been me learning jekyll from scratch, and although it is an easy-to-learn site generator, it is difficult to diagram the two-year work again and apply the updates and fixes that have been suggested to me. In the future I hope to have all my work here exposed as well as options so that third parties can leave their contributions to this growing personal project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 01:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/new-penrose/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/new-penrose/</guid>
        
        <category>information</category>
        
        <category>page</category>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        
        <category>information</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Agoraphobia</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2020 was plagued by one of the most impressive setbacks of recent times: the COVID-19 pandemic. With the arrival of the virus, &lt;strong&gt;restriction measures&lt;/strong&gt;  in circulation were implemented as an attempt to contain the contagion. in other words: we are all ordered to wait at home as long as possible. After almost 4 months of containment, it is increasingly difficult to remember &lt;strong&gt;what the world was like before&lt;/strong&gt;, it is strange to stop to think about how the world works now and how it worked a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staying at home has been a challenge to the mental stability of many people who have been subjected to social isolation. People begin to lose patience after months of staying at home, but the panic generated by an invisible killer also grows. Fear of the virus has led some to assume &lt;strong&gt;ridiculous habits&lt;/strong&gt; of hygiene and consumerism, and has even gone so far as to cause a &lt;strong&gt;phobia of public places: agoraphobia&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;technique&quot;&gt;Technique&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main layer is a style transfer applying a &lt;em&gt;“where’s wally?”&lt;/em&gt; cartoon pattern with a &lt;strong&gt;mixed color palette&lt;/strong&gt;. The other layers were different filter dimensions applied in Deep Dream convolutional networks. At the end the image is &lt;strong&gt;processed again&lt;/strong&gt; to apply hue filter, HDR and white balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-artist&quot;&gt;From the artist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pandemic keeps us alert and waiting for a catastrophe that has taken hundreds of thousands of lives around the world today. The confinement keeps us in captivity and &lt;strong&gt;forces us to be calm&lt;/strong&gt; when all the signs we receive from the outside world &lt;strong&gt;invite&lt;/strong&gt; us to panic and disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it occurred to me to create the image I was thinking about how to represent the &lt;strong&gt;state of alert&lt;/strong&gt; from a calm and &lt;strong&gt;contemplative&lt;/strong&gt; position. My cat &lt;em&gt;Pi&lt;/em&gt; was nearby and I saw him observing a feather that fell near the outside sidewalk of the house, in front of the living room window. He was lying on the edge of the back of the sofa, without tension in the muscles, but with his eyes wide open in expectation of any uninvited movement. I found it curious that &lt;strong&gt;despite expressing a state of persecution&lt;/strong&gt; with his eyes, &lt;em&gt;Pi&lt;/em&gt;’s pose never stopped being that of a sleepy cat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a photo of him and decided to use it as my main template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;models-and-references&quot;&gt;Models and references&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;models&quot;&gt;Models&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pi - my male cat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 20:23:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/image/2020/05/23/agoraphobia.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/image/2020/05/23/agoraphobia.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>image</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
