<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Penrose Trip</title>
    <description>This website is an interactive portal for informative use, which seeks to open a space for the juxtaposition between psychedelia, science, programming and art.
</description>
    <link>http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 19:32:23 -0300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 19:32:23 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tentaciones y demonios</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The representation of the devil in the Tarot is usually linked to &lt;strong&gt;creativity, desire and carnality&lt;/strong&gt;. Lust and temptation are but facets of an irascible driving force that lies in the &lt;strong&gt;human will&lt;/strong&gt;. Free will is the opportunity that randomness gives us to interact with the cosmos in the way that our desire dictates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;technique&quot;&gt;Technique&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast superposition of more than 20 layers of &lt;strong&gt;convolutional neural network designs&lt;/strong&gt; and recognized paintings in the infernal field of art.
The convolution of most of the layers was done with Deep Dream, a smaller portion was treated with Style Transfer and the other layers were only processed by color shades. The main layer is a photo without prior treatment, so the original features of this can still be differentiated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-artist&quot;&gt;From the artist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model in the picture is a friend of mine whom I have always admired for promoting the culture of temptation. I am referring to the ambit of &lt;strong&gt;reflecting sensuality&lt;/strong&gt; through the mirror and attracting curious glances without involving direct interest. Just as I mentioned before, my intention with the piece is to reflect the &lt;strong&gt;mischief of carnality&lt;/strong&gt; as a side effect of an amazingly &lt;strong&gt;complex mind&lt;/strong&gt;.
I would never consider myself as a model that inspires eroticism, but this does not make me alien to this one. The representation of desire is also an art and although I do not get very close to the conventional representation of lust, the relationship with the figure of the beast is only a mental bridge with the Tarot myth that I wanted to introduce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;models-and-references&quot;&gt;Models and references&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;models&quot;&gt;Models&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kevin Andrade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pictures&quot;&gt;Pictures&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Fall of the damned&lt;/em&gt; - Peter Paul Rubens - &lt;strong&gt;1620&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Defeat of Sennacherib&lt;/em&gt; - Peter Paul Rubens - &lt;strong&gt;1612&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Death of Sardanapalus&lt;/em&gt; - Eugene Delacroix&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;signorcasaubon&lt;/em&gt; - Marten de Vos-Hell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 20:15:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/image/2020/06/10/tentaciones-y-demonios.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/image/2020/06/10/tentaciones-y-demonios.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>image</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Penrose Trip: A whole new universe</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Penrose Trip&lt;/strong&gt; is a non-profit site whose purpose is to leave &lt;em&gt;interesting questions&lt;/em&gt; loose on the streets of the modern world with the only hope of generating even more doubts. The aim is to touch sensitive fibers regarding the compartmentalization of human thought, since the definition of the line between art and science is challenged. Of course, the strong &lt;strong&gt;psychedelic component&lt;/strong&gt; of this project cannot be ignored, and it is in this context of perpetual hallucination that the aesthetics of artificial intelligence and randomness make sense; in a world &lt;strong&gt;out of focus&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goodbye-old-penrose&quot;&gt;Goodbye, old Penrose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project has been carried out only by me since the creation of the page in the free hosting services of Github in 2018. The page’s first approach was as an image gallery, but with the time it became a gallery of my work and, therefore, an interactive portfolio. It had been carried out with simple HTML pages, with poor Javascript and CSS, and to be honest it was not so pretty aesthetically. This was acceptable as long as it was a portal for personal use, but now that it is more open to the public and even serving as a teaching tool for some Hackathon events, it can only mean one thing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;special-ad&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;

&lt;b style=&quot;font-size:19px&quot;&gt; It is time to migrate to a whole new universe &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-migrate&quot;&gt;How to migrate?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;well, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jekyll is a static site generator. You give it text written in your favorite markup language and it uses layouts to create a static website. You can tweak how you want the site URLs to look, what data gets displayed on the site, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-Jekyll Website&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll allows a simple implementation for static pages that allows to segregate posts (like this one) by themes, tags, etc. It is a simple and efficient way to migrate &lt;strong&gt;Penrose Trip&lt;/strong&gt; with enough requirements for online execution and storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-future&quot;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been almost 3 weeks since the migration started and I’m still getting warm. Much of this time has been me learning jekyll from scratch, and although it is an easy-to-learn site generator, it is difficult to diagram the two-year work again and apply the updates and fixes that have been suggested to me. In the future I hope to have all my work here exposed as well as options so that third parties can leave their contributions to this growing personal project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 20:15:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/information/2020/06/09/penrose-trip-a-whole-new-universe.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/information/2020/06/09/penrose-trip-a-whole-new-universe.html</guid>
        
        <category>information</category>
        
        <category>page</category>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        
        <category>information</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Agoraphobia</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2020 was plagued by one of the most impressive setbacks of recent times: the COVID-19 pandemic. With the arrival of the virus, &lt;strong&gt;restriction measures&lt;/strong&gt;  in circulation were implemented as an attempt to contain the contagion. in other words: we are all ordered to wait at home as long as possible. After almost 4 months of containment, it is increasingly difficult to remember &lt;strong&gt;what the world was like before&lt;/strong&gt;, it is strange to stop to think about how the world works now and how it worked a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staying at home has been a challenge to the mental stability of many people who have been subjected to social isolation. People begin to lose patience after months of staying at home, but the panic generated by an invisible killer also grows. Fear of the virus has led some to assume &lt;strong&gt;ridiculous habits&lt;/strong&gt; of hygiene and consumerism, and has even gone so far as to cause a &lt;strong&gt;phobia of public places: agoraphobia&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;technique&quot;&gt;Technique&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main layer is a style transfer applying a &lt;em&gt;“where’s wally?”&lt;/em&gt; cartoon pattern with a &lt;strong&gt;mixed color palette&lt;/strong&gt;. The other layers were different filter dimensions applied in Deep Dream convolutional networks. At the end the image is &lt;strong&gt;processed again&lt;/strong&gt; to apply hue filter, HDR and white balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-artist&quot;&gt;From the artist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pandemic keeps us alert and waiting for a catastrophe that has taken hundreds of thousands of lives around the world today. The confinement keeps us in captivity and &lt;strong&gt;forces us to be calm&lt;/strong&gt; when all the signs we receive from the outside world &lt;strong&gt;invite&lt;/strong&gt; us to panic and disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it occurred to me to create the image I was thinking about how to represent the &lt;strong&gt;state of alert&lt;/strong&gt; from a calm and &lt;strong&gt;contemplative&lt;/strong&gt; position. My cat &lt;em&gt;Pi&lt;/em&gt; was nearby and I saw him observing a feather that fell near the outside sidewalk of the house, in front of the living room window. He was lying on the edge of the back of the sofa, without tension in the muscles, but with his eyes wide open in expectation of any uninvited movement. I found it curious that &lt;strong&gt;despite expressing a state of persecution&lt;/strong&gt; with his eyes, &lt;em&gt;Pi&lt;/em&gt;’s face never stopped being that of a sleepy cat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a photo of him and decided to use it as my main template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;models-and-references&quot;&gt;Models and references&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;models&quot;&gt;Models&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pi - my male cat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 15:23:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/image/2020/05/23/agoraphobia.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/image/2020/05/23/agoraphobia.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>image</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2D Cellular Automata Lab</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;cellular automaton&lt;/strong&gt; is a system in which a grid of cells determines its state (ON or OFF) according to rules established on the states of a determined &lt;strong&gt;neighborhood&lt;/strong&gt; of cells in the grid. The system behaves according to a &lt;strong&gt;set of game rules&lt;/strong&gt; that commands each cell in the grid to adopt in the net step a state based on the previous states of the neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Game rules are codified in a structure similar to DNA. Each cell has 8 neighbors, so there are 9 states each cell hast to handle (including own state). As each one of these states are values 0 (OFF) or 1 (ON), the number of different possible neighborhood configurations, or cases, are 2 to the power of 9, or 512. Each configuration has a response ,for example, if the immediate  left neighbor is ON, then this cell turns ON as well. If we assign each one of this states to a position in a 512-length string, and in this string we store the response, the result is a 512-length string of 0’s and 1’s describing the behavior of the system. This might be codified to be expressed as genes in the form of alphanumeric values and colors. This 512-string is called the “rule code”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that &lt;strong&gt;a single rule code&lt;/strong&gt; describes the &lt;strong&gt;unique behavior&lt;/strong&gt; of a system and, moreover, there exist as much as 2&lt;sup&gt;512&lt;/sup&gt; possible rule code configurations. In other words, there are more than &lt;abbr title=&quot;An octillion is 10 to the power of 27&quot;&gt;10 octillion octillion octillion octillion octillion&lt;/abbr&gt; possible systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In almost all the processes we see in the modern world, the behavior of &lt;strong&gt;organized growth and modularity&lt;/strong&gt; seem to be somehow present. But this is not where this concept originates, because even when humanity lived in caves we noticed the patterns that nature followed around us. In the flowers, in the roots, in the clouds, in the butterfly wings, in the thunders, in the swarms: the world is full of patterns that in one way or another can be reduced to simple modules following the same rules over and over time; the phenomenon can be &lt;strong&gt;reduced&lt;/strong&gt; to the implementation of cellular automata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans are designed to notice patterns even if they are not there, but when they are, we marvel at imagining the reason for their existence. One way in which we were able to explain the reason for many patterns present in nature was to &lt;strong&gt;formulate the problem as a cellular automaton&lt;/strong&gt;, a system of individual modules programmed to follow the same rules that may or may not allow interaction between the agents of the system. This way of modeling complex problems serves to compartmentalize complex behaviors and define them as simple rules that are repeated over and over again &lt;strong&gt;out of synchronicity&lt;/strong&gt;. A swarm of simple machines that can express complexity from the interaction between themselves, conditioned to &lt;strong&gt;react to their environment&lt;/strong&gt; in a pre-defined way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intention when creating this laboratory was to offer tools to program the behavior of a cellular automaton to &lt;strong&gt;anyone&lt;/strong&gt; who is interested in the subject and is &lt;strong&gt;not trained in programming&lt;/strong&gt; (Not of all us can be nerds, right?). This laboratory is a simple and &lt;strong&gt;interactive&lt;/strong&gt; reduction of what it means to program a cellular automaton and creates an environment of &lt;strong&gt;free experimentation&lt;/strong&gt;, allowing to propose new inventions that can be modeled at will or found by chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the day to day the idea of ​​cellular automaton grazes our heads and many times &lt;strong&gt;we do not stop to observe enough&lt;/strong&gt; to formulate an idea. Cellular automata are interesting concepts that challenge the imagination and logic without the need to go exclusively into the mathematical field. This universality of applications makes this study area to be full of surprises for those who decide to venture into the dynamic world of modularity and the emergence of complex behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I built this specific gene codification was, in a beginning, a way to &lt;strong&gt;store compressed data&lt;/strong&gt; information of the state, but as experimentation went on I realized common behaviors tend to be stored in the same Gene. experimentation with cellular automaton is easy and fun as long as you find &lt;strong&gt;the beauty of the patterns&lt;/strong&gt; made by simple binary rules. These systems are controversial in the study of life emergence and complex systems, for example, you may know the famous &lt;strong&gt;Conway’s Game of Life&lt;/strong&gt; which is an specific rule code for 2D cellular automata that resembles organic movement from simple configurations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENTER&lt;/strong&gt; : Runs/Stops the simulation .&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; : Create random rule code (Random DNA button).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt; : Evolves a single step (Step button).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; : Toogles bombing (switch random cell every generation).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; : Mutates a random gene.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; : Switches the state of a random cell.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; : Sets all cells to OFF (Blank button).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; : Inverts the value of every cell.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt; : Sets the center Cell to ON.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;H / V / D / A&lt;/strong&gt; : Sets an alternating pattern along the central (Horizontal / Vertical / Diagonal / Antidiagonal) respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0 / 1&lt;/strong&gt; : create a rule code with only 0 / 1 respectively (Empty DNA button).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2/3/4&lt;/strong&gt; : Sets a figure of ON cells in the center.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/PenroseTrip/assets/sketches/cellular-automata/2d-cellular-automata.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
TEST SKETCH
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 09  / may / 2020&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 02:02:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/sketch/2020/05/06/2D-cellular-automata-lab.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/sketch/2020/05/06/2D-cellular-automata-lab.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>automata</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Flocking Ecosystem</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If we reduce life to its most &lt;strong&gt;essential components&lt;/strong&gt;, exploring the multiverse of possible interaction mechanisms becomes more intuitive when viewing each part of the whole as a simple set of &lt;strong&gt;binary rules&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swarming behavior&lt;/strong&gt; is a pattern with which we are familiar and which we can easily recognize in a flock of birds or in a school of fish, that’s why it’s called &lt;strong&gt;Flocking algorithm&lt;/strong&gt;. The truth is that this &lt;strong&gt;complex behavior&lt;/strong&gt; can arise from three simple orders that govern each individual of the simulation: a point entity (or &lt;em&gt;Boid&lt;/em&gt;) in a 2D space with a velocity vector assigned and is &lt;strong&gt;only aware of its close vicinity&lt;/strong&gt;, as well as the velocity vector of its neighbors. These three orders to &lt;em&gt;rule them all&lt;/em&gt; are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Separation :&lt;/strong&gt; Avoid crowding neighbors (short range repulsion)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alignment :&lt;/strong&gt; Steer towards average heading of neighbors (align the velocity vector)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cohesion :&lt;/strong&gt; Steer towards average position of neighbors (long range attraction)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Steering&lt;/em&gt; is applying an acceleration vector, which is a result of polling the positions and velocities of the near neighbors, to the actual velocity of the boid. All the boids follow these instructions in an infinite loop, updating steer, velocity and position values according to their current vicinity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When dozens of boids are left to wander a 2D space with  &lt;abbr title=&quot;what goes out  of one edge, comes in through the opposite edge&quot;&gt;periodic conditions&lt;/abbr&gt;, they start forming swarm-like groups that move coherently. There can be many swarms in the space and furthermore, these groups are not stable in population since colliding groups or swarms that pass near enough may change the group dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of behavior and rules have been studied for decades: it has been studied as &lt;em&gt;flocking&lt;/em&gt; in multiple scenarios, dimensions and rule variations. The original architecture of the flocking algorithm I used is based on the one developed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://natureofcode.com/book/chapter-6-autonomous-agents/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Daniel Shiffman&lt;/a&gt; in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mhjuuHl6qHM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Flocking behavior was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=86iQiV3-3IA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;simulated&lt;/a&gt; on a computer in &lt;strong&gt;1987&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Craig Reynolds&lt;/strong&gt; with his simulation program, &lt;strong&gt;Boids&lt;/strong&gt;. This program simulates simple agents (boids) that are allowed to move according to a &lt;strong&gt;set of basic rules&lt;/strong&gt;. The result is akin to a flock of birds, a school of fish, or a swarm of insects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;– Wikipedia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/PenroseTrip/assets/img/posts/sketch-organism-img1.png&quot; alt=&quot;image of boid system&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My contribution to the algorithm with which this sketch works consists of special boids that have the ability to change an internal state of normal boids, these special new boids are going to be called &lt;strong&gt;Shifters&lt;/strong&gt;, since they shift their neighbors. There are three types of Shifters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They freeze boids (or reduce their mobility) and turn them blue, allowing them to create connections with other nearby blue boids. This makes it look like the knitter is knitting a net.
heal infected boids (red or blue). They can steal speed from nearby boids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Flockers:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; They infect boids by turning them red and more strongly linked to other red boids. This causes them to behave as a tightly bound unit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;Knitters:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; They freeze boids (or reduce their mobility) and turn them blue, allowing them to create connections with other nearby blue boids. This makes it look like the knitter is &lt;em&gt;knitting&lt;/em&gt; a net &lt;sub&gt;(pun not intended)&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Healers:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; They heal infected boids (red or blue). They can steal speed from nearby boids. They may also switch velocities direction (but not magnitude) with a boid while interacting with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shifters do not like to interact with shifters of different species, but interact normally with same species shifters and other boids. They have a contagion probability associated, which means that not all interactions will result in a contagion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I knew what programming is, I have learned a few interesting concepts here and there, but over time and reviewing the development that my sketches have led, I have noticed something quite obvious now: I am low-key obsessed with &lt;strong&gt;random behaviors&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;emergence of complexity&lt;/strong&gt;. The flocking algorithm is characterized because it precisely achieves this task:  to represent an &lt;strong&gt;aggregate, complex and organic behavior&lt;/strong&gt; that arises from individuals following simple rules and interacting in the same space. And well, it has been known for a long time that it is beautiful and that it seems like happy little birds and fish moving in a group, but only doing that can not escalate more when it comes to complexity and can not give birth to &lt;strong&gt;unexpected behavior&lt;/strong&gt;. The flocking simulation is a wonderful concept in the study of the &lt;strong&gt;reduction of natural phenomena&lt;/strong&gt; through programming, but it also leaves you with a mouthful of so many potential uses that just sticking with the original rules would be a waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that the proposal will generate new discussions around the &lt;strong&gt;organic behavior&lt;/strong&gt; of autonomous agents with simple programming. There are perspectives that reconcile programming and logic with nature and all its splendor, and &lt;strong&gt;generating a dialogue&lt;/strong&gt; about it is the first step in asking the right questions that point in more &lt;strong&gt;interesting directions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the introduction of the new boids, new parameters are added to the simulation and therefore the behavior grows in complexity. When I did the first experiment I was surprised because, despite not knowing what to expect, I found new behaviors that my human perception was able to recognize and that, unless they are products of my volatile imagination, represent a new way of &lt;strong&gt;adding complexity&lt;/strong&gt; to the system. A few insights of what can be noticed at a glance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flockers and healers can each form groups of boids around them, moving as a group that can affect more boids. Despite the fact that flockers and healers cannot interact with each other (and even repel each other a little), certainly the groups formed by these can be brought together in &lt;strong&gt;larger groups&lt;/strong&gt; where boids, flockers and healers &lt;strong&gt;coexist&lt;/strong&gt;, using cohesion with the normal boids as a force that &lt;strong&gt;counteracts&lt;/strong&gt; the aforementioned repulsion. I like to think of this scenario as ca reduced case of &lt;em&gt;symbiosis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;knitters freeze boids that, if they are very close to other frozen boids, are connected between them with a line (the connection or flata of it does not affect the simulation at all, it is just a visual element). When solitary moving boids (healthy or infected by flockers) pass near these nets they naturally try to react at the speed of their neighbors. These, when stopped or moving very slowly, cause the boid to stop as well, &lt;strong&gt;being trapped&lt;/strong&gt; by the static influence of the network.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knitters usually stay near the net as an effect of the net static influence, but not always they remain static as trapped boids. They keep moving in the net surroundings until a boid gets near enough to interact and modify the knitter velocity. This perturbation, in addition with the aligning force present in every boid, causes the knitter to stop being &lt;em&gt;dormant&lt;/em&gt; and ‘Hunt’ new boids that get stuck in the near net. Sometimes perturbations in a far point in the net are propagated due to the proximity of the &lt;em&gt;net boids&lt;/em&gt; between them, causing the dormant knitter to react even if the new boid is trapped not so near.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Healers may pass through small healthy groups of boids, even using its boids to &lt;strong&gt;catapult themselves forward&lt;/strong&gt; by stealing speed. Bigger groups catch the healers easier and since it &lt;strong&gt;usually swaps speeds&lt;/strong&gt; with his neighbors, having a healer within the group usually &lt;strong&gt;helps keeping boids aligned&lt;/strong&gt; in the same direction. This feature also represents &lt;strong&gt;formation of larger groups&lt;/strong&gt; when there are flockers and healers within the group, since flockers are more likely to separate form the group due to weak aligning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/PenroseTrip/assets/img/posts/sketch-organism.gif&quot; alt=&quot;image of boid system with shifters&quot; class=&quot;post-midimage-across&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DRAG the cursor through the screen to generate new neutral boids pointed in random directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates Flocker in the cursor current position&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;H :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates Healer in the cursor current position&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K :&lt;/strong&gt; Creates Knitter in the cursor current position&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mobile&quot;&gt;Mobile&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TOUCH AND DRAG to create new boids.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SHAKE device to create random shifter in random XY position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/PenroseTrip/assets/sketches/flocking-ecosystem/flocking-ecosystem.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
TEST SKETCH
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 13  / apr / 2020&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 04:20:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/sketch/2020/04/13/flocking-ecosystem.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/sketch/2020/04/13/flocking-ecosystem.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>space</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>random</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>IMFERYE: A quest for legacy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;a group of settlers is left in an unexplored world with the aim of creating a global empire over the years. Name unexplored terrain, evolve your cities and above all have fun creating an empire as big as you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;random map&lt;/strong&gt; is generated using Perlin’s Noise including random resource sources in the field. The resource field is also generated using perlin noise but using a detail index more suitable for smaller sports (more detail in noise shape). The game maintains randomness to generate many elements of the game such as events and map conditions among other things, however, other elements such as names depend on a component associated with the immediately previous city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each town &lt;strong&gt;consumes&lt;/strong&gt; according to its size and is also capable of producing &lt;strong&gt;resources&lt;/strong&gt; if it’s on a resource spot The idea of the game is to &lt;strong&gt;expand the empire&lt;/strong&gt; as much as possible without being consumed by its own size, taking into account &lt;strong&gt;unexpected events&lt;/strong&gt; and quick growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything, except the creation of new towns, is generated with &lt;strong&gt;random numbers&lt;/strong&gt; or has to do with some random value. This is an interesting feature because it allows you to have a &lt;strong&gt;variety of situations&lt;/strong&gt; within the framework of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially when I created the project I wanted to practice a new concept that I just learned: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perlin_noise&quot;&gt;Perlin’s noise&lt;/a&gt;. An interesting concept for &lt;strong&gt;someone who loves randomness as much as I do&lt;/strong&gt;, since it is noise that is &lt;strong&gt;locally consistent&lt;/strong&gt; but &lt;strong&gt;globally random&lt;/strong&gt;. Putting it to the test I realized that in two dimensions it is easy to create cut points in the magnitude of the noise, thus creating borders on the 2D surface that enclose spots and their size depends on the cut point.
These spots turned them into islands and eventually continents. From there it was easy to start due to the structure of objects subjected to the random map map generated. The project was refined on several occasions until it became the Imferye that it is now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I directed the project in this direction because it gave me a bit of morbidity to think about our &lt;strong&gt;history as an intelligent species&lt;/strong&gt; on planet earth, and how much of that history we have lost at the hands of violent humanity, unexpected events or even bad luck. &lt;strong&gt;Modeling the legacy&lt;/strong&gt; as a way to quantify lost culture seems to me one of the most interesting details of the game: being able to observe the reasons why a civilization can put aside its most historic cities for important reasons and thus losing legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to think that the format of the game helps to &lt;strong&gt;pose the growth of a civilization as an expansion&lt;/strong&gt; originated in a center, a cancer of roads and houses that expands through unexplored terrain. Based on these ideas, I imagine how the names of cities are established in the legacy of those who founded them, in how tradition and language are &lt;strong&gt;dragged and mutated&lt;/strong&gt; by an accelerated expansion to the rhythm of consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more literary sense that the game has, I also wanted to pose a &lt;strong&gt;management challenge&lt;/strong&gt; to anyone who dares to play it. The game puts the player in a situation where  &lt;strong&gt;not always&lt;/strong&gt; taking  the most intuitive choices  prevent the empire from falling apart. The game itself is not the great strategy puzzle, but considering that it was done by one person on p5 I can say that I am proud of this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game ended up being everything I had hoped for: an alive puzzle and a temporary pet. The estimated playing time is &lt;strong&gt;half an hour&lt;/strong&gt; and although it is not a lot, it is a game that can give surprises despite its simplicity. That estimated half hour is taking into account that the player manages to keep his civilization alive for &lt;strong&gt;at least 20,000 years&lt;/strong&gt;, and in fact it is difficult to do it when there is no defined strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name generator was not as outstanding as other processes in the game, since the construction of syllables repeatedly produces huge blocks of vowels or consonants that cannot be added to a word without making sense of it. Sure, the &lt;strong&gt;alien context&lt;/strong&gt; of the game offers the right environment to ignore linguistic details to a certain extent, but it would be &lt;strong&gt;much more comfortable for the player&lt;/strong&gt; to be able to recognize their cities by a name that they can at least pronounce. I promise I will fix it, don’t lose faith in me, anonymous reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning you can put a seed corresponding to the point from which your initial tribe will originate, &lt;strong&gt;the initial point HAS to be on a beach&lt;/strong&gt;. Each new settlement that is put on the map must be connected to a nearby station, each station will increase its rank as it connects more and more stations to itself. After managing to create 5 metropolis, the game will give more seeds to originate new clans without the need to be connected to other nearby points (this new clans must be used on a beach, far from all other settlements).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CLICK :&lt;/strong&gt; create a new settlement on the map.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K :&lt;/strong&gt; (While hovering the mouse over a settlement) Inflicts damage on the settlement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A :&lt;/strong&gt; Activates auto-exploration. While active random settlements are created near existing ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;V :&lt;/strong&gt; Activates the virus. Random cities will suffer damage while active.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;indicators&quot;&gt;Indicators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROFIT &lt;em&gt;(Colored vertical bar)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; : Index of wealth in your empire. High Profit means good economical times, negative profit means austerity and may lead to famine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seeds :&lt;/strong&gt; How many seeds to start new clans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Map :&lt;/strong&gt; Which map configuration are you watching.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Difficulty :&lt;/strong&gt; Map difficulty, a good start is around 60%;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Growth :&lt;/strong&gt; Grow rate of your civilization.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Population :&lt;/strong&gt; Total number of citizens in your empire.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fuel Production :&lt;/strong&gt; Total fuel points production per year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food Production :&lt;/strong&gt; Total food points production per year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consume :&lt;/strong&gt; Total consume per year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Active/Total :&lt;/strong&gt; Active cities versus total cities placed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lost Legacy :&lt;/strong&gt; Lost cultural content. Time between your first settlement and your oldest active city.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oldest city :&lt;/strong&gt; Oldest active city.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Origin :&lt;/strong&gt;Age of the fist placed city. Years since the beginning of the game.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;line-content&quot; style=&quot;width:30%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type :&lt;/strong&gt; Type of settlement according to size and advancement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Age :&lt;/strong&gt; Age of the settlement in years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pop. :&lt;/strong&gt; Population of the settlement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rank :&lt;/strong&gt; Importance of the city. Relevant to evolve cities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clan :&lt;/strong&gt; Name of the clan that owns the city.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rate :&lt;/strong&gt; Score assigned according to city relevance in the empire.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Savings :&lt;/strong&gt; Amount of goods saved.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Era :&lt;/strong&gt; Period of time in which the empire faces an specific affair.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips&quot;&gt;Tips&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The connectivity range of the stations changes according to their type: larger cities, larger ranges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During golden times you are able to build on water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The savings will increase faster if your profit is high&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While building on water, deeper oceanic floor implies higher consume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Towns built in mountains may have a higher consume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Era changes each 4000 years approximately.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Final score depends on empire expansion, legacy and profit history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/PenroseTrip/assets/sketches/imferye/imferye.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
PLAY GAME
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 21  / may / 2019&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 06:03:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/sketch/2020/03/23/imferye-the-game.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/sketch/2020/03/23/imferye-the-game.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>game</category>
        
        <category>random</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Eigenvalue of myself</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;success&lt;/strong&gt; in facing the daily dilemmas and the occasional unexpected catastrophes that &lt;strong&gt;chance&lt;/strong&gt; places in our path depends on our ability to focus our &lt;strong&gt;superior intellect&lt;/strong&gt; on the study of our &lt;strong&gt;own being&lt;/strong&gt;. Embracing many points of view of the self is a masterful tool for &lt;strong&gt;forging&lt;/strong&gt; any new link with the world. The understanding of being is a practice that the 21st century has put aside despite being in these moments of &lt;strong&gt;cultural mishmash&lt;/strong&gt; when we most need to look within ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anyone who remains with a single perspective of the world is condemned to wander it on one only path.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technique&quot;&gt;Technique&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manual filter of facial transformation as the main template. The other layers are made up of patterns &lt;strong&gt;added by collage&lt;/strong&gt; and Deep Dream patterns added by contrast. The final image was processed &lt;strong&gt;multiple times&lt;/strong&gt; by low-enhancing convolutional filters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-artist&quot;&gt;From the artist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be said to be my version of a &lt;em&gt;“self-portrait”&lt;/em&gt;. A purely subjective representation of what I observed when analyzing my position in the world. I like to represent myself with multiple eyes because I associate them with &lt;strong&gt;knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;the occult&lt;/strong&gt;. For the latter’s purposes, I also often include in many of my pieces patterns with sacred geometry and ancestral symbology, as well as &lt;strong&gt;semasiological links&lt;/strong&gt; between the myths of tarot, religion and divine science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;models-and-references&quot;&gt;Models and references&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;models&quot;&gt;Models&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Myself - Paipa Psyche (David Paipa)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 09:26:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/image/2020/02/12/eigenvalue-of-myself.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/image/2020/02/12/eigenvalue-of-myself.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>image</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>La pantalla grande</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When transcending the world involves &lt;strong&gt;capturing an image&lt;/strong&gt; of it and reinterpreting it before the masses, man must turn to art. The performing arts are essentially the way we have found to transport the &lt;strong&gt;great stories&lt;/strong&gt; of the world over time and space, making use of our communicative faculties as &lt;em&gt;homo sapiens sapiens&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technique&quot;&gt;Technique&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple style transfer layers and Deep Dream layers applied to the &lt;strong&gt;same template&lt;/strong&gt; and overlapping them with different contrasts and opacities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-artist&quot;&gt;From the artist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model in the picture is an old friend who chose to study film and television production. Although we don’t talk to each other very much, we get along very well and whenever we can meet we talk about infinity of topics without any discomfort. He pointed out to me that, as humans, our only real way of &lt;strong&gt;transcending&lt;/strong&gt; is in the image that others have of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Telling stories&lt;/strong&gt; with movies and capturing an &lt;strong&gt;emotional footprint&lt;/strong&gt; in people have as a common factor that they can preserve a memory for much longer than the time of an average life. The world is a mix of &lt;strong&gt;unexpected events&lt;/strong&gt; in real time and &lt;strong&gt;projections&lt;/strong&gt; of past memories that we refuse to let die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;models-and-references&quot;&gt;Models and references&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;models&quot;&gt;Models&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mateo Herrera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 18:16:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/image/2020/02/10/la-pantalla-grande.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/image/2020/02/10/la-pantalla-grande.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>image</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Persona</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, most of the world’s social interactions occur thanks to &lt;strong&gt;massive information networks&lt;/strong&gt; that allow users to capture their identity on their virtual profile and expose themselves to the eyes of the world. While this often helps the masses &lt;strong&gt;keep up&lt;/strong&gt; with a world that is advancing by leaps and bounds, this lends itself to many unwanted scenarios of deception and false self-esteem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sometimes we forget about how important is to be more interesting in real life than whoever you are on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When creating a &lt;strong&gt;persona&lt;/strong&gt; in social networks, we rarely stop to think how much we want this new social network to infiltrate our lives. We do not know how much we are willing to &lt;strong&gt;share authentically&lt;/strong&gt; and when we least think about it we are showing our Sunday breakfast to 600 strangers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technique&quot;&gt;Technique&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collage in 32 Layers exposed to Style Transfer, color-filtered and re-processed with CNN to increase resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-artist&quot;&gt;From the artist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this work I wanted to reflect our &lt;strong&gt;innocence and ingenuity&lt;/strong&gt; when facing a tool as powerful on so many levels of our society as the internet is. We are barely intelligent apes that managed to create a &lt;strong&gt;network of shared knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;, and now that we have managed to expand it to all the recesses of our daily life, we tenderly have the &lt;strong&gt;illusion&lt;/strong&gt; of knowing what we are doing and where we are going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a sentient human being and observer of my environment, it is easy for me to notice that, as humankind, we are atrophying. When watching a sunset we prefer to take out the phone and see it through the screen, instead of simply marveling at the sublime vision that is presented to us. Sometimes we make a bigger effort to make a good post on social media than to support a loved one through a crisis. We create fake news to manipulate the masses, when the only effect they have is to confuse and illiterate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We choose to ignore how ignorant they have made us.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image shows the explorer crossing the threshold of the unknown that, ironically, is also full of gazes. A swirling and diffuse vision of a &lt;strong&gt;multicolored cosmos of possibilities&lt;/strong&gt; that can amaze anyone with a pair of eyes. The innocence of Ikaro flying closer and closer to the sun, not knowing that his ignorance of the situation would cost him everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;models-and-references&quot;&gt;Models and references&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;models&quot;&gt;Models&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aldo G. Dorantes (Ph.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 20:32:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/image/2019/12/14/persona.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/image/2019/12/14/persona.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>image</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2D Waves as an effect of phase in oscillators</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A 2D wave that turns out to be much more than it seems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sketch&quot;&gt;The Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When studying oscillatory phenomena, it is important to consider their three most important attributes: their &lt;strong&gt;amplitude&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;frequency&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;phase&lt;/strong&gt;. The amplitude corresponds to the intensity of the wave in terms of &lt;strong&gt;energy&lt;/strong&gt;. If the case was a sound wave, the amplitude corresponds to the volume. The frequency measures the &lt;strong&gt;periodicity&lt;/strong&gt; of the oscillations, that is, the interval of time it takes for the system to return to its &lt;strong&gt;initial state&lt;/strong&gt;. at higher frequency, the oscillator is expected to move faster. And lastly the phase, this is just a small adjustment in the oscillator time response. Since each oscillator changes as a &lt;strong&gt;function of time&lt;/strong&gt;, the phase can be seen as slightly delaying or advancing the clock of an oscillator with respect to the proper time of simulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sketch is a set of &lt;strong&gt;circular oscillators&lt;/strong&gt; of fixed size, implying &lt;strong&gt;fixed amplitude&lt;/strong&gt;, arranged in a grid and whose phase depends on its distance from the &lt;strong&gt;center of the screen&lt;/strong&gt;. This induces a change in the position of each oscillator; the further the oscillator is from the center of the screen the more noticeable the desychronization. Despite the fact that all the oscillators move at the &lt;strong&gt;same frequency&lt;/strong&gt;, that is, they rotate at the &lt;strong&gt;same speed&lt;/strong&gt;, the phase effects generate another &lt;strong&gt;macro wave effect&lt;/strong&gt; that is reflected as a circular 2D wave. This effect is due to the modeling of the phase with respect to the distance from the center of the screen and how said distance grows with &lt;strong&gt;radial symmetry&lt;/strong&gt; around said center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-purpose&quot;&gt;The Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studying the waves one eventually finds that they can be described as &lt;strong&gt;circular static oscillators&lt;/strong&gt; with a phase shift associated with their position within the system. This is accomplished with simple mathematical proofs that aim to expose a simple but powerful truth about waves, and that is that they generally do &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; transport matter, but &lt;strong&gt;energy&lt;/strong&gt;. This is a concept introduced early in the career of a physicist-in-training: the fact that each wave present in a &lt;strong&gt;composite system&lt;/strong&gt; is a generalized effect of out-of-phase oscillations of its elements. In water, for example, the creation of waves can be mathematically expressed as a set of particles that oscillate together and whose offset gives rise to a new oscillation expressed in terms of the &lt;strong&gt;group speed&lt;/strong&gt; of said particles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my perspective as a novice physicist and artist, all the oscillating movements that are present in nature represent the constant pulse of a universe that allowed itself the whim of having &lt;strong&gt;at least&lt;/strong&gt; a temporal dimension. The seasons, the Earth’s orbit, the water cycle, seismic waves, sea waves, gravitational waves, all &lt;strong&gt;linked dependently to time&lt;/strong&gt; and without it would have no reason to exist. Life itself responds to a cyclical process that is maintained until the moment of death, and even there, the &lt;strong&gt;natural cycle&lt;/strong&gt; continues, returning us to the earth and creating new life from this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t need to have the latest tools to measure ripples and notice that we are part of an &lt;strong&gt;endless cycle&lt;/strong&gt;, that we are secondary gears of a greater mechanism. The &lt;em&gt;bhagavad gita&lt;/em&gt; as an ancient text already introduces the idea of the &lt;strong&gt;natural cycle&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;eternal cycle&lt;/strong&gt; of return to which souls are subject and whose effect on earth is &lt;strong&gt;reincarnation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although wave effects are studied from physics and mathematics, waves and cycles represent a deeper link with nature from human experience. They remind us that time is a carriage that does not stop and that, despite that, it is possible to start again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An arrangement of what appear to be colored LEDs that vibrate synchronously, drawing a 2D circular wave as an effect of the phase between them. The result is a &lt;strong&gt;tool to play&lt;/strong&gt; with the phase effects in an oscillator system, teaching a little about how this phenomenon arises in
correlated oscillator systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, with this sketch people will most likely learn more about the limits of their own mind in psychedelics than about waves and cycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-controls&quot;&gt;The Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MOVE the cursor through the window to change relative phase between oscillators (change the amount of phase added relative to position)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mobile&quot;&gt;Mobile&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TOUCH and DRAG through the screen to change relative phase between oscillators&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latest-release&quot;&gt;Latest Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/PenroseTrip/assets/sketches/wave/wave.html&quot; class=&quot;link-sketch&quot;&gt;
&lt;span&gt;
TEST SKETCH
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest commit : 07  / oct / 2019&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 16:23:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/sketch/2019/10/07/wave-as-a-phase-effect.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://penrosetrip.com/PenroseTrip/sketch/2019/10/07/wave-as-a-phase-effect.html</guid>
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
        <category>visual</category>
        
        <category>p5</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>concentric</category>
        
        <category>physics</category>
        
        
        <category>sketch</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
